<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
    <title>Linux Impact</title>
    <link href="https://linuximpact.com/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://linuximpact.com" />
    <updated>2023-11-11T16:16:23+00:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>David Rutland</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://linuximpact.com</id>

    <entry>
        <title>Why we publish with Publii with GitHub Pages: it&#x27;s trouble-free and it&#x27;s actually free</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Rutland</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://linuximpact.com/why-we-publish-with-publii-with-github-pages-its-trouble-free-and-its-actually-free/"/>
        <id>https://linuximpact.com/why-we-publish-with-publii-with-github-pages-its-trouble-free-and-its-actually-free/</id>
        <media:content url="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/42/printing-press.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="Tips"/>
            <category term="Software"/>
            <category term="Self-hosted"/>
            <category term="Raspberry Pi"/>
            <category term="Linux"/>
            <category term="Internet"/>

        <updated>2023-11-11T16:16:23+00:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/42/printing-press.jpg" alt="Blurred newspapers rolling off a printing press " />
                    Self-hosting sites and services from home is a pleasure and a joy - as well as being an all-consuming hobby that gives us more headaches than it should. The Raspberry Pi 4B is more than capable of providing extensive services for an extended family -&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/42/printing-press.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="Blurred newspapers rolling off a printing press " /></p>
                <p data-pm-slice="1 1 []">Self-hosting sites and services from home is a pleasure and a joy - as well as being an all-consuming hobby that gives us more headaches than it should.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Raspberry-Pi-Computer-Suitable-Workstation/dp/B0899VXM8F/ref=sr_1_3?crid=16G7DHNEVDVBH&amp;keywords=raspberry+pi+8gb&amp;qid=1699266630&amp;sprefix=raspberry+pi+8gb%252Caps%252C152&amp;sr=8-3&amp;_encoding=UTF8&amp;tag=thecrowuk-20&amp;linkCode=ur2&amp;linkId=0f9dee46e8b8e6c27a2421c530833bac&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Raspberry Pi 4B</a> is more than capable of providing extensive services for an extended family - furnishing them with an <a href="https://linuximpact.com/self-host-your-own-audio-library-with-audiobookshelf/">Audiobook server</a>; streaming movies, shows, and music through Jellyfin; office suite and slot-in Drive replacement through courtesy of NextCloud; a <a href="https://social.rutland.org.uk/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Fediverse</a> server (eschewed by everyone but this writer); an email server and Snappymail frontend; and even more services that we can't recall right now.</p>
<p>The humble Pi has even, in the past, been used to host public-facing websites.</p>
<p>Hosting a website from home is a gratifying and traumatic experience, and your experience will vary depending on exactly how you decide to set it up.</p>
<p><a href="https://thecrow.uk/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Crow</a> - a site now on semi-permanent hiatus, and from which several of the articles on Linux Imact were culled - was created as a static site using Jekyll. The writing was done in the Atom editor, and files were shuffled off onto the Pi using SCP (Secure Copy).</p>
<p>Most of the time, the site ticked along happily, and was relatively unperturbed even under heavy traffic - one notable exception being when traffic to an article about <a href="https://thecrow.uk/A-Gov.uk-site-dedicated-to-porn-Absolutely/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">porn being hosted on a Department of Transport subdomain</a> forced the site onto a VPS for a short period.</p>
<h2 id="h-wordpress-on-a-pi-isnt-always-the-optimal-solution">WordPress on a Pi isn't always the optimal solution</h2>
<p><a href="https://linuximpact.com">Linux Impact</a> is younger than you may think - popping into existence after a domain name purchase on November 6th 2023, and certain decisions were made in an unconsidered rush.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/42/old-linux-impact.jpg" alt="An ugly Wordpress site with red and grey colour scheme" width="1680" height="774" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/42/responsive/old-linux-impact-xs.jpg 300w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/42/responsive/old-linux-impact-sm.jpg 480w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/42/responsive/old-linux-impact-md.jpg 768w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/42/responsive/old-linux-impact-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/42/responsive/old-linux-impact-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/42/responsive/old-linux-impact-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure>
<p>The first of these was to use WordPress as a content management system. WordPress is great software, and there's a reason it powers more than half of the websites online today.</p>
<p>It was...fine. It's easy to get a website looking <em>OK</em> quickly, and there's no messing around with text editors.</p>
<p>And everything worked well until we start getting decent amounts of traffic. After appearing on the HN front page, we were quickly forced offline - struggling under numbers that a static site would have handled with ease.</p>
<p>Yes, we could have eased the burden by using a CDN to deliver images and other content from elsewhere on the web, and we did seriously consider doing exactly that.</p>
<p>But once we arrived at the realisation that it wasn't entirely practical to completely host this website on a bargain basement SBC and a domestic internet connection, we started to wonder why we were hosting it at home in the first place.</p>
<h2 id="h-making-better-design-decisions">Making better design decisions</h2>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/42/designer.jpg" alt="" width="1680" height="840" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/42/responsive/designer-xs.jpg 300w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/42/responsive/designer-sm.jpg 480w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/42/responsive/designer-md.jpg 768w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/42/responsive/designer-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/42/responsive/designer-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/42/responsive/designer-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure>
<p>The first decision we made was that <em>all</em><strong><em> </em></strong>content was going to be hosted offsite. <a href="https://pages.github.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">GitHub Pages</a> was the natural choice, as hosting is both free and fast - although there's an ever present nagging feeling that current owner, Microsoft, will, at some point, pull the rug and spiral into service enshitification.</p>
<p>You can host any content you like on Github Pages. You can use your own domain name, and they'll even throw in SSL certs for free. It's pretty easy to set up, with the only proviso being that the content needs to be static. If you're hosting a web shop, or anything that requires users to sign in, static sites probably aren't for you anyway.</p>
<p>While WordPress is excellent as a content management system, and it's possible to create a site using WorPress and export it as static pages, it's a bit fiddly for our tastes, and we've always found messing around with themes, layouts and widgets to be an annoyance rather than a feature.</p>
<p>Jekyll was an option. Writing Markdown and creating sites with Jekyll is fun, but now that Atom, our favourite text editor has been archived, it's not as much fun as it used to be.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/42/publii-marketplace.jpg" alt="The Publii marketplace showing a selection of themes" width="1680" height="840" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/42/responsive/publii-marketplace-xs.jpg 300w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/42/responsive/publii-marketplace-sm.jpg 480w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/42/responsive/publii-marketplace-md.jpg 768w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/42/responsive/publii-marketplace-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/42/responsive/publii-marketplace-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/42/responsive/publii-marketplace-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure>
<p>Publii is a static site generator with all the bells and whistles you can imagine, and a for producing and editing posts, it's not all that different from the back-end of a WordPress blog: convenience, a variety of editors, a marketplace for themes and plugins. While our WordPress instance was periodically dropping offline and heroically resurfacing, we were able to port our meagre content into Publii, and get set up for free on GitHub.</p>
<h2 id="h-creating-static-sites-is-simple-with-publii">Creating static sites is simple with Publii</h2>
<p>Publii is Free software licensed under GPL3. This means you can use it, distribute, modify, and redistribute with your own modifications (provided any modifications are distributed under the same license) however you want. You can buy, sell, and trade copies if you want - although that seems kind of pointless since the developers have made binaries for Windows, MacOS, and Linux available from the main <a href="https://getpublii.com/" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">Publii website</a>.</p>
<p>Installation on our Debian-based system was as easy as popping a terminal and entering:</p>
<pre><code>wget https://getpublii.com/download/Publii-0.44.0.deb
sudo dpkg -i https://getpublii.com/download/Publii-0.44.0.deb</code></pre>
<p>...and in a matter of minutes the app was installed and accessible from the system menu (it's a fairly hefty package, so the actual download took around 300 seconds ).</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/42/publii-create-site.jpg" alt="Create new site dialogue, showing icons, Site name and author name" width="1680" height="840" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/42/responsive/publii-create-site-xs.jpg 300w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/42/responsive/publii-create-site-sm.jpg 480w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/42/responsive/publii-create-site-md.jpg 768w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/42/responsive/publii-create-site-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/42/responsive/publii-create-site-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/42/responsive/publii-create-site-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure>
<p>Start Publii, and you'll be asked to accept the GNU GPL3 license then be asked to give your website a name, and choose a name for the primary author. You can also choose an adorable little icon to represent yourself and the site within Publii. We went with a steaming hot cup of coffee. Hit the big blue button and get started.</p>
<p>This is where our experience most likely differed from most Publii users, because we weren't creating a website from scratch - we already had our struggling WordPress instance.</p>
<p>Following the very well-written and understandable Publii instructions, we logged into WordPress, and from the admin panel clicked <strong>tools &gt; export</strong> to download an XML file containing posts, authors, category, and tag content. The file itself is only a few hundred kilobytes, so took only moments.</p>
<p>Adding our exported content to Publii took longer. The process itself is simple, just click <strong>Tools &amp; Plugins &gt; WP Importer</strong>, then select the file you just downloaded. Publii will then download addition assets from your WordPress instance.</p>
<p>As our WordPress site was failing under weight of numbers, this took a good hour, and when it was over, we breathed a sigh of relief.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/42/publii-posts.jpg" alt="Publii posts view showing titled posts stacked vertically" width="1680" height="719" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/42/responsive/publii-posts-xs.jpg 300w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/42/responsive/publii-posts-sm.jpg 480w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/42/responsive/publii-posts-md.jpg 768w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/42/responsive/publii-posts-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/42/responsive/publii-posts-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/42/responsive/publii-posts-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure>
<p data-pm-slice="1 1 []">You'll find all of your posts under the <strong>Posts</strong> menu item on the left of the screen. Publii comes with a sigle them installed - it's called <strong>Simple</strong>, and it looks pretty much how you'd expect. If you want more themes, check out the <a href="https://marketplace.getpublii.com/" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">Publii marketplace</a> for a selection of free and paid-for themes.</p>
<p>We decided to go with <a href="https://marketplace.getpublii.com/themes/technews/" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">TechNews</a> - it's clean, it's smart, it's easily customised, and best of all for an experimental publication with a tight budget, it's free.</p>
<p>Download the theme zip file to your local drive, click the three dots in the top right corner of Publii, click <strong>Themes</strong>, then <strong>Install Theme</strong>.</p>
<p>To activate your new theme, Go to <strong>Site Settings</strong>, and select your new theme from the dropdown menu. Click on <strong>Save and Preview</strong> to have Publii generate the HTML for your site and open it in your default browser.</p>
<p>We noticed that some of our code snippets weren't rendering properly, and a few of our header images hadn't downloaded and had to manually fix a few issues. It wasn't a big deal.</p>
<p>In the <strong>Posts</strong> section, you'll see that you have a choice of editors, and depending on your previous experiences and preference, you can use Markdown, a word processor-ish WYSIWYG interface, or a very WordPress-like block editor.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/42/wysiwyg-2.jpg" alt="We've actually becoming unexpectedly attached to the WYSIWYG editor" width="1680" height="721" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/42/responsive/wysiwyg-2-xs.jpg 300w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/42/responsive/wysiwyg-2-sm.jpg 480w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/42/responsive/wysiwyg-2-md.jpg 768w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/42/responsive/wysiwyg-2-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/42/responsive/wysiwyg-2-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/42/responsive/wysiwyg-2-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure>
<p>Creating and editing a post is exactly what you're used to.</p>
<p>Menus, were next and similarly simple to set up, a Matomo analytics plug-in, and we were ready to go.</p>
<h2 id="h-uploading-linux-impact-to-github-pages">Uploading Linux Impact to Github Pages</h2>
<p>You'll need an account to use Github Pages, and fortunately for us, we already had one.</p>
<p>Create a new repository, and a initialise a new branch for your static files (you can delete the master branch). Make sure you have Git installed on your local machine, and to make things a little easier <strong>GitHub Desktop</strong> can be useful as well.</p>
<p>Once you've cloned the repo onto your local machine, it's simply a case of going to <strong>Server</strong> in Publii, giving your site a URL, and choosing the output type and directory. Handy hint: Don't use relative URLS or you won't get an RSS feed. Once that's done, hit <strong>Sync your Website</strong> to create the static files. Copy them over to your local GitHub repo, then push to origin.</p>
<p>Your new static site will be accessible on Github (Our Github pages address is <a href="https://davidrutland.github.io/linuximpact" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">https://davidrutland.github.io/linuximpact</a>), but you probably want to use your own domain name.</p>
<p>Visit your registrar, and enter a CNAME record with your Github pages address as the value eg: davidrutland.github.io.</p>
<p>You'll also need to create four new <strong>A </strong>records, with <strong>@</strong> as the host, and the following values:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>185.199.108.153</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>185.199.109.153</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>185.199.110.153</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>185.199.111.153</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Set the TTL as low as possible and save, then head back over to GitHub. Click <strong>Settings &gt; Pages</strong>,  and replace the yourname.github.io with your domain name. Wait for GitHub to run its checks, and make sure to click the <strong>Enforce HTTPS</strong> box.</p>
<p>That's it. You're done, and provided you don't run into any issues, it's taken may half an hour.</p>
<p>Any time you want to add or update a page, just press that <strong>Sync your Website</strong> button in Publii, and then use either Git in your terminal or Github desktop to update your site.</p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Play the first ever text adventure game in your Linux terminal!</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Rutland</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://linuximpact.com/play-the-first-ever-text-adventure-game-in-your-linux-terminal/"/>
        <id>https://linuximpact.com/play-the-first-ever-text-adventure-game-in-your-linux-terminal/</id>
        <media:content url="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/40/colossal-ibm.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="Terminal"/>
            <category term="Linux"/>
            <category term="Gaming"/>
            <category term="CLI"/>

        <updated>2023-11-10T16:56:31+00:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/40/colossal-ibm.jpg" alt="Colossal cave adventure displayed on cool retro term. Blurry white writing on a glitchy background" />
                    Back in the day, computers were serious machines for serious people doing serious things, and almost always reserved for the military, for banking, and for communications. They were huge, room-sized behemoths with capabilities that paled into insignificance next to even children's electronic toys from more&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/40/colossal-ibm.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="Colossal cave adventure displayed on cool retro term. Blurry white writing on a glitchy background" /></p>
                <p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Back in the day, computers were serious machines for serious people doing serious things, and almost always reserved for the military, for banking, and for communications.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>They were huge, room-sized behemoths with capabilities that paled into insignificance next to even <a href="https://linuximpact.com/cheap-portable-retro-gaming-with-a-hated-handheld/" data-type="post" data-id="355">children's electronic toys from more than a decade ago</a>.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>ARPANET (Advanced Research Projects Agency Network) was a project as serious as its name suggests and was the world's first distributed packet-switched network. It was designed to continue functioning even if parts of it were destroyed in a nuclear war, and would guarantee continued communication if the worst should happen.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:image {"id":387,"sizeSlug":"large","linkDestination":"none"} --></p>
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><figure class="wp-image-387"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/40/pdp-10-1-1024x512.jpg" alt="a wall-sized computer with blinking lights and huge tape reels" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/40/responsive/pdp-10-1-1024x512-xs.jpg 300w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/40/responsive/pdp-10-1-1024x512-sm.jpg 480w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/40/responsive/pdp-10-1-1024x512-md.jpg 768w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/40/responsive/pdp-10-1-1024x512-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/40/responsive/pdp-10-1-1024x512-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/40/responsive/pdp-10-1-1024x512-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure></figure>
<p><!-- /wp:image --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>The project employed some of the brightest and most brilliant minds of the mid 20th century, and bright, brilliant people tend to get bored easily.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>While modern workers might surreptitiously open minesweeper or solitaire, computer games weren't really a thing in 1976. Sure, electronic<em> Tic Tac Toe</em> had been around since 1950, and <em>Spacewar!</em> arrived on the scene in 1962, but there was nothing really truly immersive.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>And so, Will Crowther - a keen Dungeons and Dragons fan and avid cave explorer, as well as having a career as a serious developer for ARPANET's very serious PDP-10 mainframe computer, designed and created Colossal Cave Adventure using FORTRAN IV.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>As the title suggests, the game takes place in a colossal cave (in reality, based on Kentucky's Mammoth cave ), filled with gold, treasure and enemies. The goal is simple: Find the treasures, defeat the enemies, and escape.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Crowther's base game was expanded on in 1977 by Stanford University hacker and programmer, Don Woods, who expanded the scenario and gameplay to include magical elements, dwarves, and further fantastical features.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Originally designed to be played on teletype printers, Colossal Cave Adventure describes the scene to you, and responds to typed commands.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Colossal Cave Adventure is rightfully regarded as one of the most influential games of all time, and spawned entire genres of derivative gaming experiences, as well as direct descendants including the classic Zork and Rogue.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2 id="h-colossal-cave-adventure-in-the-modern-world" class="wp-block-heading">Colossal Cave Adventure in the modern world</h2>
<p><!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:image {"id":388,"sizeSlug":"large","linkDestination":"none"} --></p>
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><figure class="wp-image-388"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/40/colossal-cave-bear-1024x512.jpg" alt="A large 3d bear with a collar and chain" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/40/responsive/colossal-cave-bear-1024x512-xs.jpg 300w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/40/responsive/colossal-cave-bear-1024x512-sm.jpg 480w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/40/responsive/colossal-cave-bear-1024x512-md.jpg 768w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/40/responsive/colossal-cave-bear-1024x512-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/40/responsive/colossal-cave-bear-1024x512-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/40/responsive/colossal-cave-bear-1024x512-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure></figure>
<p><!-- /wp:image --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>The game was an instant hit, and was released and re-released for a variety of platforms that didn't require building-sized infrastructure, Microsoft Adventure was published for Apple computers in 1979, with a version for IBM PCs following in 1981.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>In 2017, a mere 41 years after Colossal Cave Adventure's initial release, the game was made open source and uploaded to <a href="https://gitlab.com/esr/open-adventure">GitLab</a>, spawning a number of remakes and reimaginings. In January 2023, a fully realised <a href="https://www.colossalcave3d.com/" data-type="link" data-id="https://www.colossalcave3d.com/">3D version was announced by Cygnus Entertainment</a>.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>At Linux Impact, we're old school, and spend more time than is good for our eyesight and health staring into terminals.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>And lacking a teletype machine, the Linux terminal seems as good a place as any to reconnect with the roots of gaming.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2 id="h-install-colossal-cave-adventure-on-linux" class="wp-block-heading">Install Colossal Cave Adventure on Linux</h2>
<p><!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Ready to commit entire months of your life to exploring an imaginary cave system in your terminal?</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>We've explored many iterations and versions of Colossal Cave Adventure (so that you don't have to), and determined Troglobit's <em>Adventure</em> to be the most reliably usable of the open source releases.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Open a terminal, then download and extract the latest archive:</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>wget <a href="https://github.com/troglobit/adventure/releases/download/v4.2/advent-4.2.tar.gz">https://github.com/troglobit/adventure/releases/download/v4.2/advent-4.2.tar.gz</a><br>tar xvf advent-4.2.tar.gz</code></pre>
<p><!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>This will create a new directory within your home directory. Move into it:</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>cd advent-4.2</code></pre>
<p><!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>You'll be building the game from source, make sure you have <em>make</em>and a compiler such as gcc installed.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Build <em>Adventure</em> with:</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>./configure<br>make</code></pre>
<p><!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>The game will install to<strong> /usr/local/bin</strong>, and the documents will end up in<strong> /usr/local/share</strong>.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>You can invoke the game's manual from the command line with:</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>man adventure</code></pre>
<p><!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>...but as the six line document states, "part of the game is to discover its rules", so there's little help there.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Start the game by entering:</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>adventure</code></pre>
<p><!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>into any terminal window.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>You can quit by typing:</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>quit</code></pre>
<p><!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Or if you want to save your progress for later, type:</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>suspend</code></pre>
<p><!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2 id="h-playing-colossal-cave-adventure-in-the-21st-century" class="wp-block-heading">Playing Colossal Cave Adventure in the 21st century</h2>
<p><!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:image {"id":390,"sizeSlug":"large","linkDestination":"none"} --></p>
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><figure class="wp-image-390"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/40/collosal-cave-retro-1-1024x512.jpg" alt="collosal cave adventure played using cool-retro-term on a 1980s style amber terminal" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/40/responsive/collosal-cave-retro-1-1024x512-xs.jpg 300w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/40/responsive/collosal-cave-retro-1-1024x512-sm.jpg 480w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/40/responsive/collosal-cave-retro-1-1024x512-md.jpg 768w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/40/responsive/collosal-cave-retro-1-1024x512-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/40/responsive/collosal-cave-retro-1-1024x512-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/40/responsive/collosal-cave-retro-1-1024x512-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure></figure>
<p><!-- /wp:image --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>OK. Let's start by saying that this is simultaneously one of the most enjoyable and frustrating gaming experiences we've had in a while. Cyberpunk 2077 it ain't.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>From the start, your options are limited, and you don't know what they are. You issue commands by typing a maximum of two words.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><strong>Look</strong> is the first command we figured out, and it gave us a written description of our environment. <strong>Take</strong>, <strong>Enter</strong>, and <strong>Eat</strong>, all have consequences, even if they're as trivial as seeing a "your feet are now wet" message after entering a stream.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>We've spent several hours exploring the colossal cave so far, and don't think we're even close to figuring out all the commands.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Yes, there are cheat sheets and maps available online, and we imagine there are walkthroughs available, too. But figuring things out as you go is a thrill all of its own, and a far cry from the tutorials and training levels of more modern games.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Later text adventures came with rudimentary graphics to illustrate your surroundings (this author's first video game experience was with the 1986 text graphical hybrid Escape From Khoshima), but the complete absence of any kind of visual clue or explicit instructions is part of the charm. It forces you to visualise your surroundings, draw maps with pen and paper, and keep extensive notes. It's a blast from the past, and somewhat similar to your computer acting as DM in a single player D&amp;D session.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>All in all, we're having a blast (from the past).</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2 id="h-enhance-your-colossal-cave-experience-with-a-retro-terminal" class="wp-block-heading">Enhance your Colossal Cave experience with a retro terminal</h2>
<p><!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>We don't have the equipment or budget to play Colossal Cave Adventure as it was originally meant to be played, but the right terminal emulator can at least give you the 1981 experience.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><a href="https://linuximpact.com/relive-the-glory-days-of-crt-monitors-with-cool-retro-term/" data-type="post" data-id="381">cool-retro-term gives your terminal the look and feel of a console run on a CRT</a> from days gone by. You might be playing on an LCD or OLED screen, but with cool-retro-term, you get scan lines, fuzz, glitches, screen burn, and more.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Presets include Apple, IBM 3278, Monochrome Green, and IBM DOS.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>We don't have a time machine, but using cool-retro-term to play Colossal Cave Adventure is the next best thing.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Relive the glory days of CRT monitors with cool-retro-term</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Rutland</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://linuximpact.com/relive-the-glory-days-of-crt-monitors-with-cool-retro-term/"/>
        <id>https://linuximpact.com/relive-the-glory-days-of-crt-monitors-with-cool-retro-term/</id>
        <media:content url="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/39/bill-bailey-ibm-dos-cool-retro-term.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="Terminal"/>
            <category term="Software"/>
            <category term="CLI"/>

        <updated>2023-11-10T17:33:26+00:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/39/bill-bailey-ibm-dos-cool-retro-term.jpg" alt="A scruffy Jack russel displayed on a glitchy terminal" />
                    Cathode ray tube televisions dominated household lounges from the beginnings of television in the early 20th century, to the widespread adoption of LCD displays in the early 21st. Most people's first experience of any kind of computer would have involved using a coaxial cable to&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/39/bill-bailey-ibm-dos-cool-retro-term.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="A scruffy Jack russel displayed on a glitchy terminal" /></p>
                <p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Cathode ray tube televisions dominated household lounges from the beginnings of television in the early 20th century, to the widespread adoption of LCD displays in the early 21st.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Most people's first experience of any kind of computer would have involved using a coaxial cable to connect an early console or home computer to the back of the family television.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Even if you were an early adopter of the fabulously expensive 'personal computers' that could be used at home, you still would have plugged it into a CRT monitor.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2 id="h-cool-retro-term-is-a-time-machine-for-your-terminal" class="wp-block-heading">Cool Retro Term is a time machine for your terminal</h2>
<p><!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:image {"id":395,"sizeSlug":"large","linkDestination":"none"} --></p>
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><figure class="wp-image-395"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/39/a1200-1024x512.jpg" alt="Amiga 1200 with a CRT monitor playing Bomb Jack" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/39/responsive/a1200-1024x512-xs.jpg 300w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/39/responsive/a1200-1024x512-sm.jpg 480w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/39/responsive/a1200-1024x512-md.jpg 768w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/39/responsive/a1200-1024x512-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/39/responsive/a1200-1024x512-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/39/responsive/a1200-1024x512-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure></figure>
<p><!-- /wp:image --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>The humble CRT monitor has an enduring place in pop culture, and aside for in the nostalgia for your own lost youth, they appear as central to the plot in a huge range of cinematic and cultural classics.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>The project aims to transport you to a simpler time and place, when a computer's memory was measured in kilobytes, and having to adjust vertical scanning to get a clear image was a daily chore, and you occasionally needed to physically whack your hardware to get it to behave.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>cool-retro-term is lightweight and immensely customisable to help you get the exact retro look and feel you're searching for.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>As well as coming with presets such as IBM, Apple, monochrome green, and futuristic, you can also configure cool retro term with visual artefacts common to technology of the last century to make your session more immersive.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2 id="h-install-cool-retro-term-on-linux" class="wp-block-heading">Install cool Retro Term on Linux</h2>
<p><!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>cool-retro-term is available is the standard repositories for most distros.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>To install cool-retro-term of Arch and its kin enter:</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>sudo pacman -S cool-retro-term</code></pre>
<p><!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Or for Debian and derivatives:</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>sudo apt install cool-retro-term</code></pre>
<p><!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>For Fedora and friends:</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>sudo dnf install cool-retro-term</code></pre>
<p><!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Alternatively, you can install cool-retro-term using the AppImage:</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>wget https://github.com/Swordfish90/cool-retro-term/releases/download/continuous/Cool_Retro_Term-dac2b4f-x86_64.AppImage</code></pre>
<p><!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Make it executable with:</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>sudo chmod +x cool-retro-term/releases/download/continuous/Cool_Retro_Term-dac2b4f-x86_64.AppImage</code></pre>
<p><!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>...and launch with:</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>./Cool_Retro_Term-dac2b4f-x86_64.AppImage</code></pre>
<p><!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2 id="h-fine-tune-your-of-vintage-computing-terminal-experience" class="wp-block-heading">Fine-tune your vintage computing terminal experience</h2>
<p><!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:image {"id":396,"sizeSlug":"large","linkDestination":"none"} --></p>
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><figure class="wp-image-396"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/39/crt-settings-1024x449.jpg" alt="Screen split vertically into two. cool-retro-term on the left, with the setings menu on the right" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/39/responsive/crt-settings-1024x449-xs.jpg 300w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/39/responsive/crt-settings-1024x449-sm.jpg 480w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/39/responsive/crt-settings-1024x449-md.jpg 768w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/39/responsive/crt-settings-1024x449-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/39/responsive/crt-settings-1024x449-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/39/responsive/crt-settings-1024x449-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure></figure>
<p><!-- /wp:image --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Early monitors had their quirks. Monochrome screens for instance, and weird lines that floated up and down the screen. Fuzzy text, burn-in. cool-retro-term recreates these faithfully.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Launch the app from your start menu or regular console, and you'll see glowing orange text on a brown background, complete with the bezel of the curved monitor on which your terminal is supposed to be running. A slow drifting line changes the hue as it lazily progresses down the screen, and static noise hints at electromagnetic interference - or possibly a dodgy tuner. There's a slight flicker. Welcome to the 1980s.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Of course, you may want your session to be more or less immersive, and if you want to alter of fine-tune any of these special effects it's easy to do:</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Right-click anywhere in the interface to bring up the context menu, then click on <strong>Settings</strong>. Under <strong>Effects</strong>, you'll see checkboxes and sliders for everything from screen curve and flickering, to ambient light, jitter, and burn-in. You can adjust these to your satisfaction or turn them off altogether.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Under the <strong>Advanced </strong>tab, you can enhance the realism by adjusting the quality of the textures, bloom and burn-in, as well as changing the frame rate of the effects. Yes, your virtual monitor can flicker and jitter with a realism of 60 FPS, but that kind of defeats the point.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2 id="h-modern-utilities-in-a-vintage-environment" class="wp-block-heading">Modern utilities in a vintage environment</h2>
<p><!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>The great thing about about using cool-retro-term is that you can use it just like a regular terminal. Edit your conf files in nano, view images with ImageMagick, create markdown documents, and write HTML for your website or blog.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Whatever you do, it will exude a kind of ineffable cyberpunk cool. It's like using the terminals in a video game, but for real, and important stuff. You're the protagonist in Fallout, or your own 80s movie. You'll find yourself frequenting coffee shops in the hope that someone will look over your shoulder and see just how excessively cool you are.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2 id="h-run-some-classic-games-in-your-retro-terminal" class="wp-block-heading">Run some classic games in your retro terminal</h2>
<p><!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:image {"id":391,"sizeSlug":"large","linkDestination":"none"} --></p>
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><figure class="wp-image-391"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/39/colossal-ibm-1024x512.jpg" alt="colossal cave adventure on cool retro term with an emulated black and white IBM screen" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/39/responsive/colossal-ibm-1024x512-xs.jpg 300w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/39/responsive/colossal-ibm-1024x512-sm.jpg 480w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/39/responsive/colossal-ibm-1024x512-md.jpg 768w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/39/responsive/colossal-ibm-1024x512-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/39/responsive/colossal-ibm-1024x512-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/39/responsive/colossal-ibm-1024x512-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure></figure>
<p><!-- /wp:image --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>While you can do virtual everything you'd normally do in cool-retro-term, we feel you'd be missing out if you didn't fully embrace the nostalgia by running some cool retro games. We'd especially recommend <a href="https://linuximpact.com/play-the-first-ever-text-adventure-game-in-your-linux-terminal/" data-type="post" data-id="384">Colossal Cave Adventure</a> - the world's first text adventure.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>How to install the latest version of Docker Compose on Linux (and why you should)</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Rutland</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://linuximpact.com/how-to-install-the-latest-version-of-docker-compose-on-linux-and-why-you-should/"/>
        <id>https://linuximpact.com/how-to-install-the-latest-version-of-docker-compose-on-linux-and-why-you-should/</id>
        <media:content url="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/38/docked.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="Tips"/>
            <category term="Terminal"/>
            <category term="Software"/>
            <category term="CLI"/>

        <updated>2023-11-10T16:57:30+00:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/38/docked.jpg" alt="A cabin cruiser docked next to a pier at sunrise" />
                    It's an understatement to say that Linux has a diverse software ecosystem. No two distros are identical, and each person's setup is unique to them in terms of both software and hardware. While this is great if you want to express your individuality and indulge&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/38/docked.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="A cabin cruiser docked next to a pier at sunrise" /></p>
                <p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>It's an understatement to say that Linux has a diverse software ecosystem. No two distros are identical, and each person's setup is unique to them in terms of both software and hardware.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>While this is great if you want to express your individuality and indulge your curiosity by running the latest niche project on DistroWatch, it makes it difficult for developers to create software for a standard Linux environment - because there isn't one.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>All software has dependencies that you need to have installed on your system before you can install certain packages. What those packages are, and what packages are available to you will vary wildly. If you're too far from 'the norm', or if the versioning isn't quite right, you could end up in dependency hell.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2 id="h-use-containers-to-create-standard-environments" class="wp-block-heading">Use containers to create standard environments</h2>
<p><!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Containerisation is the solution to situations where managing dependencies can become excessively complex, problematic, and error-prone.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Instead of creating and releasing a single app, developers while produce a container that includes everything the app needs to run. This can include pre-configured databases, dependencies pinned to a certain version, or even full-blown operating system bases.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>While there are many container orchestration tools, Docker is the most commonly used, and the ancillary project, Docker Compose, allows you to define and run multi-container Docker applications. With Docker compose, you can manage any number of local or web-facing applications, with nothing more than a simple markup file, and some easy-to-recall commands.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2 id="h-install-docker-on-debian-ubuntu-and-raspberry-pi-os" class="wp-block-heading">Install Docker on Debian, Ubuntu, and Raspberry Pi OS</h2>
<p><!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Docker is available in the standard repositories, and there are rarely any breaking changes from the most recent version (at least we've never heard of any ). To install Docker on any Debian derived system, open a terminal, and enter</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><code>sudo apt install docker.io</code></p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Docker runs as a privileged daemon, with root powers. You'll need to add your user to the Docker group in order to summon it:</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><code>sudo usermod -aG docker your_username</code></p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Now log out and back in again for the changes to take effect</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2 id="h-dont-install-docker-compose-from-the-default-repository" class="wp-block-heading">Don't install Docker Compose from the default repository!</h2>
<p><!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:image {"id":377,"sizeSlug":"large","linkDestination":"none"} --></p>
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><figure class="wp-image-377"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/38/flaming-shipwreck-1024x512.jpg" alt="A sailing boat on file at a dock. The dock is also on fire" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/38/responsive/flaming-shipwreck-1024x512-xs.jpg 300w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/38/responsive/flaming-shipwreck-1024x512-sm.jpg 480w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/38/responsive/flaming-shipwreck-1024x512-md.jpg 768w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/38/responsive/flaming-shipwreck-1024x512-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/38/responsive/flaming-shipwreck-1024x512-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/38/responsive/flaming-shipwreck-1024x512-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure></figure>
<p><!-- /wp:image --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Docker compose is a different kettle of fish entirely, and while most projects will run just fine if you install Docker Compose with:</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>sudo apt install docker-compose</code></pre>
<p><!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Some won't, and we've seen an increasing number of failures where deploying a project requires excessive workarounds. Rather than an orderly cargo port, you're faced with a burning shipwreck instead.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>If you're running into inexplicable problems with deploying apps when using a repo-installed version of Docker Compose, first uninstall it:</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>sudo apt remove docker-compose</code></pre>
<p><!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Visit the Docker Compose GitHub releases page, scroll down to <strong>Assets</strong>, and locate the correct package for your system architecture.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:image {"id":376,"sizeSlug":"large","linkDestination":"none"} --></p>
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><figure class="wp-image-376"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/38/docker-compose-releases-1-1024x453.jpg" alt="Assets section of the docker-compose releases page showing linux packages" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/38/responsive/docker-compose-releases-1-1024x453-xs.jpg 300w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/38/responsive/docker-compose-releases-1-1024x453-sm.jpg 480w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/38/responsive/docker-compose-releases-1-1024x453-md.jpg 768w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/38/responsive/docker-compose-releases-1-1024x453-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/38/responsive/docker-compose-releases-1-1024x453-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/38/responsive/docker-compose-releases-1-1024x453-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure></figure>
<p><!-- /wp:image --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>If you're not sure, you can find out your system architecture by typing:</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>uname -m</code></pre>
<p><!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>...into a terminal.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>In the case of our 64-bit Raspberry Pi 4B, this command will return <strong>aarch64</strong>, so we'd look for the <strong>docker-compose-linux-aarch64</strong> package.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>If you have a modern desktop or laptop, it's likely that you need <strong>docker-compose-linux-x86_64</strong>.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Download the relevant package, locate it in your terminal, then move it into your path:</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>mv docker-compose* /usr/local/bin/docker-compose</code></pre>
<p><!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Now make it executable with:</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>sudo chmod +x /usr/local/bin/docker-compose</code></pre>
<p><!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>That's all you need to do. You now have the most recent Docker Compose version installed!</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Use it to install and run some awesome self-hosted projects such as <a href="https://linuximpact.com/install-immich-on-a-raspberry-and-replace-google-photos/" data-type="post" data-id="282">Immich</a> - a better <a href="https://linuximpact.com/immich-is-the-killer-app-that-will-kick-start-the-self-hosting-revolution/" data-type="post" data-id="293">self-hosted Google Photos alternative</a>, or <a href="https://linuximpact.com/self-host-your-own-audio-library-with-audiobookshelf/" data-type="post" data-id="225">host your own audiobook library with Audiobookshelf</a>!</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Cheap portable retro-gaming with a hated handheld</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Rutland</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://linuximpact.com/cheap-portable-retro-gaming-with-a-hated-handheld/"/>
        <id>https://linuximpact.com/cheap-portable-retro-gaming-with-a-hated-handheld/</id>
        <media:content url="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/37/mk-on-leapster-gs.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="Linux"/>
            <category term="Hardware"/>
            <category term="Gaming"/>
            <category term="DIY"/>

        <updated>2023-11-10T17:35:50+00:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/37/mk-on-leapster-gs.jpg" alt="" />
                    If you were a kid in the early 1990s, you'll remember the gaming revolution that was the Nintendo Game Boy. Sure, there were portable gaming systems before - the Game &amp; Watch in particular springs to mind - but these were single game units. You&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/37/mk-on-leapster-gs.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>If you were a kid in the early 1990s, you'll remember the gaming revolution that was the Nintendo Game Boy. Sure, there were portable gaming systems before - the Game &amp; Watch in particular springs to mind - but these were single game units. You could play Donkey Kong or Chef, or if you were really swish, the double screened Super Mario Bros.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>But you could play thousands of titles on a Game Boy - thanks to its cartridge system that meant you were, in essence, carrying a console in your pocket.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Later Game Boy models and other manufacturers brought handheld gaming into the mainstream, and it was rare to see a classroom without a few suspiciously bulging pockets stuffed with GBAs, PSPs, and who can can forget the Sega Game Gear? (Answer: everyone).</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:image {"id":356,"sizeSlug":"large","linkDestination":"none"} --></p>
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><figure class="wp-image-356"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/37/coke-game-gear-1024x518.jpg" alt="A red sega Game gear with Coca Cola Branding" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/37/responsive/coke-game-gear-1024x518-xs.jpg 300w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/37/responsive/coke-game-gear-1024x518-sm.jpg 480w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/37/responsive/coke-game-gear-1024x518-md.jpg 768w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/37/responsive/coke-game-gear-1024x518-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/37/responsive/coke-game-gear-1024x518-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/37/responsive/coke-game-gear-1024x518-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure>
<figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Not everything goes better with Coke | Credit: <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Coca_Cola_Game_Gear_(8567377373).jpg">Chapuisat from España</a>, <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">CC BY 2.0</a>, via Wikimedia Commons</figcaption>
</figure>
<p><!-- /wp:image --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>With modern phones, everyone has a console in their pocket, and emulators proliferate on the various app stores - allowing the avid retro-gamer access to legendary Game Boy games, and console classics through to the 2000s.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>But gaming on a phone is soulless. and no touchscreen can ever compare to the solid tactility of real buttons. Yes, you can buy<a href="https://www.amazon.com/Android-PC-Nintendo-Switch-PS4-iOS/dp/B0CGCJXSLX?&amp;_encoding=UTF8&amp;tag=thecrowuk-20&amp;linkCode=ur2&amp;linkId=efb0ce1827f7c159766948a7a066bd74&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325"> phone attachments to give you joypad-like controls</a>, but it's not the same.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2 id="h-parents-loved-the-leapster-gs-kids-not-so-much" class="wp-block-heading">Parents loved the Leapster. Kids? Not so much.</h2>
<p><!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:image {"id":357,"sizeSlug":"large","linkDestination":"none"} --></p>
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><figure class="wp-image-357"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/37/pink-leapster-1024x512.jpg" alt="A small boy wearing headphones with a pink Leapster. A parent watches on. " sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/37/responsive/pink-leapster-1024x512-xs.jpg 300w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/37/responsive/pink-leapster-1024x512-sm.jpg 480w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/37/responsive/pink-leapster-1024x512-md.jpg 768w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/37/responsive/pink-leapster-1024x512-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/37/responsive/pink-leapster-1024x512-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/37/responsive/pink-leapster-1024x512-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure>
<figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Credit: <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Leapster_2.jpg">Lana</a>, <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">CC BY 2.0</a></figcaption>
</figure>
<p><!-- /wp:image --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>The teens of the 90s became the parents of the 2010s, and to paraphrase Red Dwarf's Dave Lister, became sensible, reliable, and other words ending with -ible.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Sure, they remembered the pocketable joys of the Game Boy, as well as the cartoonish violence available on other consoles, and they thought to themselves, "Why not give our children the same as we had, but more educational and less fun?"</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>And thus was born the Leapfrog Leapster series of handheld consoles. The Leapster GS entered the world in 2012, and for a handheld kids' toy had fairly decent specs. Internal storage was measured in the low gigabytes, and its 500 MHz processor meant that it was, in theory, more powerful than Sony's still-in-production Playstation 2. The screen, though small, was a usable touchscreen and stylus, with good colour even in broad daylight. It had buttons and a D-pad designed for gaming. There was even a camera!</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Like the Game Boy series, Leapster GS games came on a cartridge. Unlike Nintendo's offerings, the games were Flash-based, and exclusively angled towards educating children between the ages of four and nine. Remember Flash? It powered most of the games on the internet for a while, and is now lost to the sands of history.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:image {"id":358,"sizeSlug":"large","linkDestination":"none"} --></p>
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><figure class="wp-image-358"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/37/leapster-gs-page-1024x505.jpg" alt="official Leapfrog sales page for the Leapster GS showing the official MRSP of $9.99" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/37/responsive/leapster-gs-page-1024x505-xs.jpg 300w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/37/responsive/leapster-gs-page-1024x505-sm.jpg 480w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/37/responsive/leapster-gs-page-1024x505-md.jpg 768w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/37/responsive/leapster-gs-page-1024x505-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/37/responsive/leapster-gs-page-1024x505-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/37/responsive/leapster-gs-page-1024x505-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure></figure>
<p><!-- /wp:image --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>If you want to buy a spanky new Leapster GS, the Leapfrog website still has them listed for the bargain price of $49.99. Games are limited, pricey, and seldom available from the official source - although you can find <a href="https://www.amazon.com/LeapFrog-McStuffins-Learning-Platinum-LeapsterGS/dp/B00D38UBJ6?&amp;_encoding=UTF8&amp;tag=thecrowuk-20&amp;linkCode=ur2&amp;linkId=821c1687ea0c67b6aff2db2e2e67bed9&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325">Disney Doc McStuffins Learning Game</a> on Amazon for $25.99.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>A quick eBay search shows a moderately active Leapster GS market place, with "spares and repairs" items with a Buy It Now price of £5, while at the upper end, a Leapster GS with a carry case and one original game is currently tagged at £45, and it doesn't even have battery packs.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>The advice we'd give is that if you can find a decent one for under £20, bag it - and give it a new lease of life as an emulation station you can fit in your pocket.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2 id="h-grab-a-used-bargain" class="wp-block-heading">Grab a used bargain</h2>
<p><!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Given that the Leapster is essentially useless to kids over the age of seven, it's not surprising that they end up being shoved to the back of a drawer until the child eventually leaves home for college, and parents have the unenviable task of sorting through two decades of discarded shit, and deciding what's actually worth keeping.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>If they've been well looked after, artefacts such as the Leapster GS tend to end up in charity shops (The British version of a Thrift store, or possibly GoodWill).</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>We were lucky enough to find an almost perfect example for a fiver in a British Heart Foundation shop near to the Linux Impact mansion. A fiver! OK, so the buttons had lost some of their paint, and it was a bit grimy, but otherwise it was in perfect nick. Even better, the four AA battery slots were filled with rechargeable cells, and it came with a charger. The lack of game cartridges to accompany the unit probably contributed to the price and failed to deter us one iota.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2 id="h-we-use-arch-btw" class="wp-block-heading">We use (Retro)Arch BTW</h2>
<p><!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Unlike certain other consoles manufacturers that go to great lengths to ensure lock-in, and that you can't use your Steam library on a PS5, Leapfrog has no such protections in place, meaning that enterprising individuals have taken the time to develop alternate firmware for the device.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Retroleap works on the LeapsterGS and LeapPad2, and combines Retroarch, ARM-optimized emulator cores, and a buildroot root filesystem.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>With Retroleap, converting the Leapfrog Leapster GS from a poorly conceived semi-educational toy to a kickass portable games console didn't take long. The biggest hurdle was finding a compatible cable.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>By the time our pocket pal appeared on the scene, Micro-USB had been the industry standard for five years, so it's kind of baffling that Leapfrog went with the older Mini USB interface. You won't find one in your local supermarket or Poundland, and they were becoming a rarity even in 2012. Fortunately, we never throw a cable away, and after an afternoon sifting through three large bin bags of electronic paraphernalia, were able to locate one that had previously been used with a digital camera.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>After that, it was a case of following the instructions on the <a href="https://github.com/mac2612/retroleap">Retroleap GitHub repo</a>:</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Making sure we had the necessary dependencies:</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>sudo apt install sg3-utils git python</code></pre>
<p><!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Cloning sshflash:</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>git clone https://github.com/mac2612/sshflash.git &amp;&amp; cd sshflash</code></pre>
<p><!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Downloading and unzipping the latest release into the sshflash directory:</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>wget <a href="https://github.com/mac2612/retroleap/releases/download/v2.0.0-alpha10/retroleap_v2.0.0-alpha10.zip">https://github.com/mac2612/retroleap/releases/download/v2.0.0-alpha10/retroleap_v2.0.0-alpha10.zip</a><br><br>unzip retroleap_v2.0.0-alpha10.zip<br><br>rm retroleap_v2.0.0-alpha10.zip</code></pre>
<p><!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:image {"id":359,"sizeSlug":"large","linkDestination":"none"} --></p>
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><figure class="wp-image-359"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/37/turning-on-the-leapster-1024x469.jpg" alt="A grimy leapster GS with fingers positioned in an awkward way" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/37/responsive/turning-on-the-leapster-1024x469-xs.jpg 300w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/37/responsive/turning-on-the-leapster-1024x469-sm.jpg 480w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/37/responsive/turning-on-the-leapster-1024x469-md.jpg 768w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/37/responsive/turning-on-the-leapster-1024x469-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/37/responsive/turning-on-the-leapster-1024x469-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/37/responsive/turning-on-the-leapster-1024x469-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure>
<figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Did we mention our unit was dirty? This was after some cleaning..</figcaption>
</figure>
<p><!-- /wp:image --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Once you have the required files, plug in the Leapster using the antique cable, and flex your fingers, because this part is hard. You have to hold both shoulder buttons, and the hint button, then press the power button. The struggle is real, and if you're anything like us, you'll spoon it completely a few times and end up on the default Leapster menu. If so, start again until you get it right.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>When the screen shows a graphic of a Leapster connected to a PC, you've managed it and can move on.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Flash the new firmware onto the Leapster with:</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>./remote_flash.sh</code></pre>
<p><!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>That's it. Your Leapster will reboot as an emulation station - capable of playing games designed for the Atari 800, NES, SNES, Sega Megadrive (Genesis), Game Boy, and Game Boy Advance.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2 id="h-add-some-kick-ass-roms-to-your-leapster-gs" class="wp-block-heading">Add some kick-ass ROMs to your Leapster GS</h2>
<p><!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>You'll be interacting with the Leapster over SSH (Secure Shell), and transferring files using SCP (Secure Copy). The IP address of the Leapster will always be <strong>169.254.6.1</strong></p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>For the sake of your own sanity, you should create some directories on the Leapster to keep things organised.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Our favourite emulator is the for the Megadrive. You can create a directory for your Megadrive ROMs with:</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>ssh -i ~/sshflash/keys/id_rsa root@169.254.6.1 'mkdir /roms/megadrive'</code></pre>
<p><!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Then transfer your massive archive of homebrew Megadrive ROMS to the new directory with:</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>scp -i ~/sshflash/keys/id_rsa /path/to/your/cool/rom.md root@169.254.6.1:/roms/megadrive/</code></pre>
<p><!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>It's that simple, and you can work out the button layout yourself.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2 id="h-the-yoof-of-today" class="wp-block-heading">The yoof of today</h2>
<p><!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:image {"id":360,"sizeSlug":"large","linkDestination":"none"} --></p>
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><figure class="wp-image-360"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/37/mk-leapster-1024x512.jpg" alt="A fight between Cyrax and Reptile in Ultimate Mortal Kombat 3 on the Leapster GS" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/37/responsive/mk-leapster-1024x512-xs.jpg 300w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/37/responsive/mk-leapster-1024x512-sm.jpg 480w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/37/responsive/mk-leapster-1024x512-md.jpg 768w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/37/responsive/mk-leapster-1024x512-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/37/responsive/mk-leapster-1024x512-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/37/responsive/mk-leapster-1024x512-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure></figure>
<p><!-- /wp:image --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>It's hard to describe the look of disdain that comes over the faces of various nephews and nieces who visit Linux Impact Towers and see the author sitting on the couch playing on a Leapster GS.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>The junior relatives are aged between five and ten, and all of them have seen Leapsters before. Some have even owned them, and they know the console as underwhelming, something their parents want them to have, and even the younger ones think its for babies. They'd rather have a Game Boy or a Switch.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>They are shocked, nay, awed, when I hand it over just in time for them to see and hear a legendary finishing move on Ultimate Mortal Kombat 3, battle through the jungles of Donkey Kong Country, unleash lightning as a god in Street Fighter 2 Turbo, or explore the world in The Legend of Zelda: A Link to the Past - arguably the greatest console game of all time.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>But is a humble Leapster GS running RetroLeap the GOAT?</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>We'd argue that yes it is. While mainstream, proper handheld consoles can run RetroArch, run the exact same games as RetroLeap, output to a TV, AND have their own exclusive titles, the price is a drawback. A top end OLED model <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Nintendo-Switch-OLED-Model-Neon-Joy/dp/B098RL6SBJ/ref=sr_1_2?crid=1CALE3PJL84YL&amp;keywords=nintendo+switch&amp;qid=1699364373&amp;sprefix=nintendo+switch%252Caps%252C169&amp;sr=8-2&amp;_encoding=UTF8&amp;tag=thecrowuk-20&amp;linkCode=ur2&amp;linkId=3fdc3efabd96b7d4e7147bba7405975e&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325">Nintendo Switch</a> will set you back $350, while a basic <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Nintendo-Switch-Lite-Turquoise-Renewed/dp/B081XLXZ4P/ref=sr_1_9?crid=1CALE3PJL84YL&amp;keywords=nintendo+switch&amp;qid=1699364373&amp;sprefix=nintendo+switch%252Caps%252C169&amp;sr=8-9&amp;_encoding=UTF8&amp;tag=thecrowuk-20&amp;linkCode=ur2&amp;linkId=550285411a6dd386c496ca68b4da86d6&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325">"renewed" Switch Lite</a> comes in at $175. It's hardly pocket money, and your average eight-year-old will have a much harder time convinced a parent or relative that it's a necessary purchase.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>But to indulge your kids with a $5 or $10 purchase, and a library of thousands of essentially free games is a different proposition altogether.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Discover your most used Linux commands with MUC</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Rutland</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://linuximpact.com/discover-your-most-used-linux-commands-with-muc/"/>
        <id>https://linuximpact.com/discover-your-most-used-linux-commands-with-muc/</id>
        <media:content url="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/36/word-cloud.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="Tips"/>
            <category term="Terminal"/>
            <category term="TUI"/>
            <category term="Software"/>
            <category term="Linux"/>
            <category term="CLI"/>

        <updated>2023-11-10T11:17:44+00:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/36/word-cloud.jpg" alt="" />
                    Life with Linux is all about the command line. While it's true that there are thousands of awesome distros and dozens of beautiful desktop environments, when it comes down to it, the Linux terminal is where things actually get done. Whether it's transferring files to&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/36/word-cloud.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Life with Linux is all about the command line. While it's true that there are thousands of awesome distros and dozens of beautiful desktop environments, when it comes down to it, the Linux terminal is where things actually get done.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Whether it's transferring files to your Raspberry Pi server using SCP, creating config files, or setting up your own Google Photos alternative, you will, more often than not, find yourself elbows deep in a black screen typing commands.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>But do you ever wonder what commands you type most often? If we had to hazard a guess, we'd say that our most commonly used Linux command is some variant of <strong>ls</strong> - the command to list the contents of a directory - but we don't know for sure.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>We're curious though, and if you, like us, are desperate to discover your top commands, along with some ancillary information, and presented in a beautiful terminal window, muc (Most Used Commands) is the terminal tool for you.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="h-why-would-you-want-to-know-your-most-frequently-used-terminal-commands">Why would you want to know your most frequently used terminal commands?</h2>
<p>
<!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:image {"id":346,"sizeSlug":"large","linkDestination":"none"} --></p>
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><figure class="wp-image-346"><img loading="lazy" src="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/36/typing-hands-1024x512.jpg" alt="hands typing on a laptop keyboard"  sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/36/responsive/typing-hands-1024x512-xs.jpg 300w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/36/responsive/typing-hands-1024x512-sm.jpg 480w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/36/responsive/typing-hands-1024x512-md.jpg 768w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/36/responsive/typing-hands-1024x512-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/36/responsive/typing-hands-1024x512-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/36/responsive/typing-hands-1024x512-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure></figure>
<p>
<!-- /wp:image --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>How about arthritis?</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>This may sound fatuous (it kinda is), but typing puts wear and tear on your fingers and joints, and often the command strings you use can be wordy. If you find out what commands you use most, you can create a short, easy-to-remember alias, and use that instead.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Also, data is beautiful. But until you have the data you can't do anything with it.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="h-how-to-install-muc-on-linux">How to install muc on Linux</h2>
<p>
<!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>muc is written with the Rust language, and while muc is available in the AUR (Arch User Repository), it isn't included in the standard repositories for any distro. The easiest way to install it is with Cargo.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>If you don't already have Rust and Cargo on your system, the devs recommend using a script to install it. Open a terminal, and enter:</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>curl --proto '=https' --tlsv1.2 -sSf https://sh.rustup.rs | sh </code></pre>
<p>
<!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Once that's out of the way, you can install muc with:</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>cargo install --git=https://github.com/nate-sys/muc</code></pre>
<p>
<!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Downloading, compiling, and installing muc took under a minute on our laptop, but significantly longer on the Linux Impact Raspberry Pi server.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="h-use-muc-to-reveal-you-most-used-commands">Use muc to reveal you most used commands</h2>
<p>
<!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:image {"id":345,"sizeSlug":"large","linkDestination":"none"} --></p>
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><figure class="wp-image-345"><img loading="lazy" src="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/36/muc-output-1024x489.jpg" alt="Linux terminal showing muc output with percentages and a bar graph"  sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/36/responsive/muc-output-1024x489-xs.jpg 300w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/36/responsive/muc-output-1024x489-sm.jpg 480w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/36/responsive/muc-output-1024x489-md.jpg 768w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/36/responsive/muc-output-1024x489-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/36/responsive/muc-output-1024x489-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/36/responsive/muc-output-1024x489-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure></figure>
<p>
<!-- /wp:image --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Once muc is installed, you can launch the program by typing:</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>muc</code></pre>
<p>
<!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>...into any terminal.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>By default, muc will use your bash history for its analysis. If it can't find the file, muc may throw an error with the message, "Could not find HISTFILE environment variable. Supply the file path with the --file option".</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>By default, your history file is located at ~/.bash-history</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>To get the full path, enter:</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>echo $HISTFILE</code></pre>
<p>
<!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Now relaunch muc with the --file option, for instance:</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>muc --file /path/to/your/history file</code></pre>
<p>
<!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="h-linux-impacts-most-used-commands">Linux Impact's most used commands</h2>
<p>
<!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>As expected our most used command was ls - accounting for more than one quarter of all commands issued. This was followed by <strong>cd</strong>, which accounted for a further fifth.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Next up was <strong>sudo</strong>, with a range of privileged commands such as <strong>apt</strong>, <strong>dpkg</strong>, and <strong>reboot</strong>.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Further down the list were further file operations, including <strong>scp</strong>, <strong>mv</strong>, and <strong>cp</strong>. This feels about right, as we tend to use the terminal in place of a file manager.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><strong>ssh</strong> is also fairly high on the list as we spend a lot of time interacting with remote machines.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Finally, we have <strong>yt-dlp</strong> for downloading streaming media, and <strong>tiv</strong>, which we use as part of a script to fetch images from a remote server and display them in a terminal in the corner of our primary workspace.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Over on the Pi, the picture was slightly different. While <strong>ls,</strong> <strong>sudo</strong>, and file operation commands still topped the list, we found a fair bit devoted to <strong>docker</strong>, <strong>nano</strong>, and various system monitoring tools.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Having satisfied our curiosity, and created various three-letter aliases for docker-compose operations, we resolved to check in with muc in a few months time to see if our usage had changed. </p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Immich is the killer app that will kick-start the self-hosting revolution</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Rutland</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://linuximpact.com/immich-is-the-killer-app-that-will-kick-start-the-self-hosting-revolution/"/>
        <id>https://linuximpact.com/immich-is-the-killer-app-that-will-kick-start-the-self-hosting-revolution/</id>
        <media:content url="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/35/a-selection-of-polaroid-photos-with-the-immich-logo.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="Software"/>
            <category term="Self-hosted"/>
            <category term="Raspberry Pi"/>
            <category term="Linux"/>
            <category term="Internet"/>
            <category term="Hardware"/>
            <category term="DIY"/>

        <updated>2023-11-11T15:48:01+00:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/35/a-selection-of-polaroid-photos-with-the-immich-logo.jpg" alt="" />
                    A killer app can drag a product or a practice from obscurity to dominance. Before the iPhone, it was weird to have a make phone calls palm-sized touchscreen computer in your pocket, and my HP Jornada 928, and various XDA devices, attracted curiosity whenever I&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/35/a-selection-of-polaroid-photos-with-the-immich-logo.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>A killer app can drag a product or a practice from obscurity to dominance. Before the iPhone, it was weird to have a make phone calls palm-sized touchscreen computer in your pocket, and my HP Jornada 928, and various XDA devices, attracted curiosity whenever I whipped it out in public.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>The iPhone normalised smartphones thanks to its hardware design, multi-touch capacitive touchscreen and a user-friendly, gesture-based interface. It dragged pocket-sized computing devices out of the hands of geeks like me and into the sunlight. These days, you'd be considered odd if you didn't have a smartphone.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>History is filled with examples of killer apps that made niche technologies mainstream, and transformed the esoteric into the norm.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>GUIs, and MS Windows in particular, made computing accessible and mundane; Office transformed actual offices; America Online (AOL) popularized email in the 1990s, making it a mainstream communication tool and driving internet adoption.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>The common feature with these technologies is that they make your life better in some way, and that they're easy to set up and use.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>I'm a self-hosting enthusiast and evangelist - perhaps even a fanatic - and I use a Raspberry Pi 4B as a server. It's a niche hobby, and one that has caused innumerable headaches over the years. Sure - thanks to Nextcloud, Jellyfin, Audiobookshelf, FreshRSS, an email server, and a few other self-hosted apps, I've managed to more-or-less break free of reliance on tech giants, but it has, at times, been difficult. It's also hard to explain to friends and relations why I do what I do, and why they should too.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>There has not, thus far, been a killer feature to bring self-hosting into the mainstream. In my opinion, that has now changed, and if there is anything that can convert your average person into buying a Pi and getting into self-hosting, Immich is it. It is <em>the</em> killer app</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Everyone's a happy snapper</h2>
<p><!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Thanks to smartphones, almost everyone takes a tonne of photos every day. There are selfies with your besties, random snaps of cute animals, what you had for dinner.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Over the last decade or so, you've probably snapped tens of thousands of images, and if you opted into the Android ecosystem, you've had them backed up automatically to Google's servers, free of charge.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Google Photos is a great product, and it got people hooked on photographing every detail of their lives. You can view your images on any phone with the app installed, or scroll infinitely through the web interface. You can search for your friends by name, or describe an object to see pictures of that cool butterfly you spotted back in 2018. It will even provide you with reminders of what you were doing on this day last year or a decade ago - affording you a depressing insight into your own aging process.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>When Google pulled the rug on unlimited free storage in 2021 - imposing a 15GB limit across all of the company's free products - it left a lot of people over their allowance, and wondering what to do about it. The easiest option, of course, was to pay Google a recurring fee.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Sure, you could host your own Google Photos alternative, but that requires technical know-how, and the results don't compare to the simple, intuitive ease and usability of Google Photos.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>I've previously recommended <a href="https://linuximpact.com/deploy-photoprism-and-host-your-own-google-photos-alternative/" data-type="post" data-id="213">PhotoPrism</a> for self-hosters looking for a Google Photos alternative. It's a great piece of software, and has served me well for several years - but it isn't Immich.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2 id="immich-is-a-google-photos-clone" class="wp-block-heading">Immich is a better Google Photos clone</h2>
<p><!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:image {"id":295,"sizeSlug":"large","linkDestination":"none"} --></p>
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><figure class="wp-image-295"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/35/immich-web-interface-1-1024x513.jpg" alt="" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/35/responsive/immich-web-interface-1-1024x513-xs.jpg 300w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/35/responsive/immich-web-interface-1-1024x513-sm.jpg 480w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/35/responsive/immich-web-interface-1-1024x513-md.jpg 768w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/35/responsive/immich-web-interface-1-1024x513-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/35/responsive/immich-web-interface-1-1024x513-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/35/responsive/immich-web-interface-1-1024x513-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure></figure>
<p><!-- /wp:image --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>The first thing you notice about Immich is that it looks good. Better than good in fact, and has clearly taken design cues from Google. If it ain't broke, don't fix it, and all that.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Show the <a href="https://demo.immich.app">Immich demo instance</a> to your mum, show it to your grandad. If they've used Google photos before, they'll recognise it instantly. It's intuitive to use. Scroll down, and see the years fly by on the right side of the screen. Click on a photo to open it fullscreen, and the information icon to get details such as the date, location, a handy map, and identities of anyone tagged. Simples.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Below is a screenshot of my old Google Photos web interface. While they do look extremely similar there are some glaringly obvious differences. The first is that it hasn't actually been used since 2020, and even then, these are WhatsApp photos automatically uploaded when I plugged in a phone I didn't even realise I still had.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:image {"id":296,"sizeSlug":"large","linkDestination":"none"} --></p>
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><figure class="wp-image-296"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/35/google-photos-web-interface-1024x514.jpg" alt="google photos web interface showing nags and images from 2020 " sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/35/responsive/google-photos-web-interface-1024x514-xs.jpg 300w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/35/responsive/google-photos-web-interface-1024x514-sm.jpg 480w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/35/responsive/google-photos-web-interface-1024x514-md.jpg 768w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/35/responsive/google-photos-web-interface-1024x514-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/35/responsive/google-photos-web-interface-1024x514-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/35/responsive/google-photos-web-interface-1024x514-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure></figure>
<p><!-- /wp:image --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>You'll notice that in the Google screenshot, I have 10GB of 15GB used. While in the Immich image, I'm currently 998.7GB of 3.6TB. Storage is cheap, and in the long run, considerably cheaper than paying a subscription fee to the big G.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>And then there are the nags, and reminders that storage is 66% full, and the constant exhortations to "Unlock storage discount or manage storage". Yeah. Screw that noise.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Up in the top right, of Google photos, you'll see a cog icon - click on it and see the top item on the settings menu is once again nagware to upgrade. Do I want to "unlock storage discount"? What does that even mean?</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Settings in Google Photos are rather meaningless and banal. In contrast, the Immich administration panel is loaded with features that you don't have to touch.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>I say that because many people - especially if they're new to running their own services - won't want to interfere with the way it works. But should you wish to, you can mess with the machine learning models, set thresholds for facial recognition, manage job concurrency, and even choose your own tile server for the map.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Did I mention the map? I thought Google Photos had this feature, but on revisiting it after several years, I can't locate it. The map is easy to find on Immich - it's the third entry on the left, it says "Map", and has a little icon of a map.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:image {"id":298,"sizeSlug":"large","linkDestination":"none"} --></p>
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><figure class="wp-image-298"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/35/immich-map-view-zoomed-in-on-Cyprus-1024x515.jpg" alt="immich map view zoomed in on Cyprus" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/35/responsive/immich-map-view-zoomed-in-on-Cyprus-1024x515-xs.jpg 300w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/35/responsive/immich-map-view-zoomed-in-on-Cyprus-1024x515-sm.jpg 480w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/35/responsive/immich-map-view-zoomed-in-on-Cyprus-1024x515-md.jpg 768w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/35/responsive/immich-map-view-zoomed-in-on-Cyprus-1024x515-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/35/responsive/immich-map-view-zoomed-in-on-Cyprus-1024x515-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/35/responsive/immich-map-view-zoomed-in-on-Cyprus-1024x515-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure></figure>
<p><!-- /wp:image --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Click on it, and you'll see numbers in various locations around the world. These separate as you zoom in - giving finer detail of exactly how many photos were taken where. When the number is low enough, you'll see thumbnails start to appear. You can click on these. Neato.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Image and facial recognition is where it's at though. Google is good at this, and so is Immich, and if you want to, you can specify the limits at which a face is recognised. You can tag people, merge faces, set birthdays, and so on. While I'd love to demonstrate how this works, the people I've tagged would probably be upset if I plastered their mugs on the internet, and an image composed entirely of smudged faces kind of defeats the point. Instead, here's a composite of the tagged page of three dogs:</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:image {"id":301,"sizeSlug":"large","linkDestination":"none"} --></p>
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><figure class="wp-image-301"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/35/immich-timeline-showing-three-tagged-dogs-1024x613.jpg" alt="immich timeline showing three tagged dogs" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/35/responsive/immich-timeline-showing-three-tagged-dogs-1024x613-xs.jpg 300w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/35/responsive/immich-timeline-showing-three-tagged-dogs-1024x613-sm.jpg 480w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/35/responsive/immich-timeline-showing-three-tagged-dogs-1024x613-md.jpg 768w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/35/responsive/immich-timeline-showing-three-tagged-dogs-1024x613-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/35/responsive/immich-timeline-showing-three-tagged-dogs-1024x613-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/35/responsive/immich-timeline-showing-three-tagged-dogs-1024x613-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure></figure>
<p><!-- /wp:image --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>That's pretty impressive, right?</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>The app is also a no brainer. Install it from F-droid, Google Play or the iphone store(?), and the only real thing you need to plug in apart from your username and password is the server URL.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>At the top of the app or web interface, Immich will even show you "memories" of this date in previous years. Click on one and it'll start a slideshow. Neat!</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Given how awesomely Immich stacks up against the alternatives, why wouldn't anyone want to host their own - especially when you remind them that Google scans their photos as a matter of routine, so privacy isn't something you have to accept as a necessary cost of easy-to-use image hosting.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2 id="immich-is-simple-to-install-and-use" class="wp-block-heading">Immich is simple(ish) to install and use</h2>
<p><!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>OK. The prospect of setting up your own Google Photos clone with unlimited storage is exciting. But most people don't consider themselves experts, and only about 3% of people use Linux. Of those, a decent proportion will be Steam Deck owners.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Outside of tech and related industries, few people have ever seen a Linux terminal that wasn't in a movie about hackers. It's scary and unfamiliar.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>The truth is that anyone can follow a set of instructions, provided they're clear enough. Copying and pasting commands isn't difficult, and if you run into problems, search engines are a thing, and there's even a friendly <a href="https://discord.com/invite/HkcuPgXVFm">Immich Discord server</a> where you can ask for advice.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>If you know what you're doing, you can start with a newly bought Raspberry Pi, and have Immich up and running in half an hour or so. If you're a complete noob, it might take you an afternoon.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>I've written a guide on how to set up Immich on a new Raspberry Pi - assuming the reader has never dabbled in the murky waters of Linux. While the article you're reading now is extolling the virtues of Immich, the <a href="https://linuximpact.com/install-immich-on-a-raspberry-pi-and-replace-google-photos/">guide to installing Immich on a Raspberry Pi</a> is designed to get you up and running as fast as possible. Although it's stripped to the bone, the guide still weighs in at around 1,500 words. Go read it (or don't - I don't care).</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Early releases of Immich required you to set a tonne of variables in an environment file. Now, it's just the uploads location. You can do just about everything through the web interface.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>I'll grant that if you've only ever used a GUI desktop environment, installing Immich on a Pi will probably scare the shit out of you, but it's doable. Take a deep breath and follow the instructions.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Maintenance is as simple as running a single command:</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>docker-compose pull &amp;&amp; docker-compose update</code></pre>
<p><!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>But just because it's relatively easy to set up, doesn't mean you're limited. If you're confident, you can fine-tune almost everything.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2 id="immich-is-creating-true-believers-and-evangelists" class="wp-block-heading">Immich is creating true believers and evangelists</h2>
<p><!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Going back to the title, I still maintain that Immich is the killer app for self-hosting. I know this because people I know have seen me using Immich, and have heard me talking about it. They've seen that my entire family group have accounts on my Raspberry Pi Immich instance and that for them, it just works.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>They're interested.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Several friends and acquaintances (Disclaimer: this writer have very few friends and acquaintances) have expressed interest in buying a Raspberry Pi, and hosting their own Immich instance.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>One friend has actually pulled the trigger, and now runs accounts for himself, his wife, and his sons. It's a start. His prior computer experience amounted to owning a badly outdated Chromebook - that he now uses to connect to the Pi via SSH.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Eventually, his friends (he has many more friends than this writer) will get curious, or complain about photo storage limits, and he'll show them what Immich is, and how easy it is to use and install. There will be more converts.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>This is how it starts.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>My Pi-owning friend is only running Immich so far, but he's already opening his mind to other possibilities, and getting into the headspace where he doesn't need to rely on Google, Amazon, Apple, or any other corp. He's talking about a mail server.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>This is how the self-hosting revolution begins.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Mealie - Probably the best self-hosted recipe manager... In the world.</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Rutland</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://linuximpact.com/mealie-probably-the-best-self-hosted-recipe-manager-in-the-world/"/>
        <id>https://linuximpact.com/mealie-probably-the-best-self-hosted-recipe-manager-in-the-world/</id>
        <media:content url="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/34/a-delicious-plate-of-food.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="Tips"/>
            <category term="Software"/>
            <category term="Self-hosted"/>
            <category term="Raspberry Pi"/>
            <category term="Linux"/>

        <updated>2023-11-10T11:17:44+00:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/34/a-delicious-plate-of-food.jpg" alt="" />
                    Self-hosted recipe managers are an essential fact of life in the Linux Impact kitchen. They solve the fundamental problem of keeping all of our recipes organised, in one place, and without the entire family history that comes with online recipes before you even get to&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/34/a-delicious-plate-of-food.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Self-hosted recipe managers are an essential fact of life in the Linux Impact kitchen. They solve the fundamental problem of keeping all of our recipes organised, in one place, and without the entire family history that comes with online recipes before you even get to the actual ingredients.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>I wrote about the problem for another site last year, and to save my poor fingers from excessive strain, I’ve copy pasta’d the crux of the issue below:</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><em><strong>We scour the net for recipes, and in the dim and distant past, we bookmarked them for later reference. Often, the page has changed or been deleted by the time we get round to looking at them again. Cooking blogs are abandoned as their owners lose interest, and individual links on active sites become invalid as the site is updated.</strong></em></p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><em><strong>Bookmarks don’t work as a long term recipe solution.</strong></em></p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><em><strong>It’s far better to print off the page, either on paper or as a PDF and keep it locally. But then, organising and searching for the right recipe becomes a chore.</strong></em></p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Self hosting a recipe manager means that you have web facing software on a server, into which you can plug a URL, and the software will fetch the recipe for you, list all the ingredients in the ingredients section, and itemise the method. It will pull the prep time and cooking time, and pull a relevant image and place it at the top of the recipe page.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>You can then follow along on your phone in the kitchen, search for and tick off items as you prowl the labyrinthine aisles of your local supermarket, and share the recipe with friends and fellow cooks.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>For the last year, Linux Impact has been using Jeppe Zapp’s excellent Nextcloud Cookbook - and it’s been great. Almost perfect, in fact.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:image {"id":202,"sizeSlug":"large","linkDestination":"none"} --></p>
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><figure class="wp-image-202"><img loading="lazy" src="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/34/nextcloud_cookbook_default_view-1024x571.jpg" alt="Nextcloud cookbook showing multiple recipes"  sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/34/responsive/nextcloud_cookbook_default_view-1024x571-xs.jpg 300w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/34/responsive/nextcloud_cookbook_default_view-1024x571-sm.jpg 480w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/34/responsive/nextcloud_cookbook_default_view-1024x571-md.jpg 768w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/34/responsive/nextcloud_cookbook_default_view-1024x571-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/34/responsive/nextcloud_cookbook_default_view-1024x571-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/34/responsive/nextcloud_cookbook_default_view-1024x571-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure></figure>
<p>
<!-- /wp:image --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">The problem with Nextcloud</h2>
<p>
<!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>I love Nextcloud. It’s the first piece of self-hosted software I installed on my first 2GB Raspberry Pi, and I still use it today for file syncing - although the Pi has been upgraded to the more competent<a href="https://amzn.to/3omPTEM"> </a><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Raspberry-Pi-Computer-Suitable-Workstation/dp/B0899VXM8F/ref=sr_1_3?crid=16G7DHNEVDVBH&keywords=raspberry+pi+8gb&qid=1699266630&sprefix=raspberry+pi+8gb%252Caps%252C152&sr=8-3&_encoding=UTF8&tag=thecrowuk-20&linkCode=ur2&linkId=0f9dee46e8b8e6c27a2421c530833bac&camp=1789&creative=9325" data-type="link" data-id="https://www.amazon.com/Raspberry-Pi-Computer-Suitable-Workstation/dp/B0899VXM8F/ref=sr_1_3?crid=16G7DHNEVDVBH&keywords=raspberry+pi+8gb&qid=1699266630&sprefix=raspberry+pi+8gb%252Caps%252C152&sr=8-3&_encoding=UTF8&tag=thecrowuk-20&linkCode=ur2&linkId=0f9dee46e8b8e6c27a2421c530833bac&camp=1789&creative=9325">8GB Raspberry Pi 4b variant.</a></p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>I could have used an <a href="https://linuximpact.com/turn-your-old-pc-or-laptop-into-a-server-and-own-your-own-piece-of-the-internet/" data-type="post" data-id="41">old laptop, a PC or almost any old computing hardware I had lying around and repurposed it as a server</a>. The advantage of using a Pi lies in its small size and its tiny power draw - essential as it’s running 24/7.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>If you wanted, you could almost completely de-google simply by using self hosted alternatives available from the Nextcloud App store. It’s honestly amazing. You can install Nextcloud on your server and never have to install another thing ever again.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>But although Nextcloud has apps for everything, they are very rarely the best at what they do.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>They are the training wheels versions of self-hosted software - all of them are quite adequate to use before you feel comfortable enough to move onto full-fat stand-alone projects.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Eventually, you begin to feel the edges of their limitations and of the limitations of Nextcloud itself. It’s a huge and monolithic piece of software, the design constraints mean that every app which runs on the platform looks more-or-less the same, and although it is not slow, the UI isn’t exactly lighting quick either.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>As a self-hoster, you’ll eventually come across other projects which do the same job - but better, or neater or in a more usable way, and over the course of months or years, your dependence on Nextcloud will fade as you spin up yet another subdomain to run new shiny services.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><a href="https://apps.nextcloud.com/apps/news">Nextcloud News</a> gives way to FreshRSS.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Nextcloud Photos is superceded by Photoprism.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><a href="https://apps.nextcloud.com/apps/music">Nextcloud Music</a> pales before <a href="https://jellyfin.org/">Jellyfin</a>.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>The functional yet uninspiring <a href="https://apps.nextcloud.com/apps/social">Nextcloud Social</a> is supplanted by a self-contained Pleroma instance.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>And now Nextcloud Cookbook is set to be replaced by Mealie. At least in my kitchen it is.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Here’s why.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="mealie-moves-fast-and-things-break">Mealie moves fast and things break</h2>
<p>
<!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><a href="https://hay-kot.github.io/mealie/">Mealie</a> is a standalone self-hosted recipe manager developed by a mysterious Alaskan known only as Hay Kot. It’s beautiful, it’s functional, and it’s fast. More importantly it’s appearance isn’t tied to whatever your Nextcloud theme is, so it’s easy to get it looking exactly how you want.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:image {"id":203,"sizeSlug":"large","linkDestination":"none"} --></p>
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><figure class="wp-image-203"><img loading="lazy" src="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/34/mealie_default-home_page-1024x564.jpg" alt="The mealie app showing a bunch of tasty recipes"  sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/34/responsive/mealie_default-home_page-1024x564-xs.jpg 300w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/34/responsive/mealie_default-home_page-1024x564-sm.jpg 480w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/34/responsive/mealie_default-home_page-1024x564-md.jpg 768w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/34/responsive/mealie_default-home_page-1024x564-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/34/responsive/mealie_default-home_page-1024x564-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/34/responsive/mealie_default-home_page-1024x564-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure></figure>
<p>
<!-- /wp:image --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>After following development since it was <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/selfhosted/comments/kp3qih/mealie_a_self_hosted_recipe_manager_alpha_release/">first announced on Reddit</a> three months ago, I finally got around to installing it on the Pi yesterday morning. The feature I had been waiting for was user authentication - meaning that internet randos couldn’t add or edit recipes to my instance without my permission. It’s my recipe manager - I don’t mind other people using it as a reference, but I don’t want to end up adding six kilos of salt to my hash brownies because someone thought it would be funny. Authentication was added in v0.40 (ten days ago) and I jumped on board at v0.41.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Are you getting a feel for the pace of development here? An alpha announcement in January and a very solid feature packed release in April. That’s pretty damned quick.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><a href="https://hay-kot.github.io/mealie/getting-started/install/">Installation</a> was a breeze - adding a few lines to my docker-compose.yml and navigating to port 9925 on the Pi gave me the interface. Setting up a reverse proxy in Apache gave me a web address for a subdomain I happened to have lying around. The entire process took maybe five minutes.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>And that’s where i ran into my first issue.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Mealie is set up with one user and default credentials - the idea is that you log in as the default user and then you can change the email and passwords, add other users, etc.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>The problem was that the default user hadn’t been created during installation. It was impossible to log in. Bummer.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>I created a <a href="https://github.com/hay-kot/mealie/issues/276">Github issue</a> explaining the problem and also hopped over to the <a href="https://discord.gg/R6QDyJgbD2">Mealie Discord server</a> just in case I was doing something stupid or had missed a step.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>My GitHub issue was answered with a temporary solution which fixed the problem, and within an hour, the dev had rolled out a new version - v0.41a - in which the issue was fixed.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>That is insane.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="whats-it-actually-like">What’s it actually like?</h2>
<p>
<!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Supernaturally fast bug-fixes aside, Mealie is a joy to use.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Navigate to port 9925 or the web address if you have a reverse proxy set up, and you’re greeted with all of your recipes displayed on cards. Hover over one to get a top line summary of the dish. Click on it, and it will give you the full thing - ingredients on the left and steps on the right. And it’s fast - far quicker than opening a recipe in Cookbook, which can take up to a whole second and a half!</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>As with Cookbook, adding recipes is as simple as plugging in a URL, then, provided the page hosting the recipe is compliant with recipe schema, it will import all the steps, ingredients, title, pictures etc.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Mealie isn’t quite as forgiving with recipes in which don’t quite meet the standard, and I’ve had a couple of imports fail - the dev is working on it. Again, consider for a second that Mealie didn’t even exist six months ago. It will get better. Alternatively, you can add recipes manually - entrusting Grannie’s secret fudge formula to Mealie’s MySQL database.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>So far, I haven’t had a lot of luck with the categories, but search works well and is quick.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Potentially, one of the best features is a meal planner. With this I can easily select meals for an entire week - or month, or whatever time period I want, and then view them by clicking on ‘Dinner Tonight’ or ‘Dinner this week.’</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:image {"id":205,"sizeSlug":"large","linkDestination":"none"} --></p>
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><figure class="wp-image-205"><img loading="lazy" src="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/34/mealie_self_hosted_meal_planner-1-1024x572.jpg" alt="The mealie meal planner with recipes for five days"  sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/34/responsive/mealie_self_hosted_meal_planner-1-1024x572-xs.jpg 300w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/34/responsive/mealie_self_hosted_meal_planner-1-1024x572-sm.jpg 480w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/34/responsive/mealie_self_hosted_meal_planner-1-1024x572-md.jpg 768w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/34/responsive/mealie_self_hosted_meal_planner-1-1024x572-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/34/responsive/mealie_self_hosted_meal_planner-1-1024x572-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/34/responsive/mealie_self_hosted_meal_planner-1-1024x572-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure></figure>
<p>
<!-- /wp:image --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Theoretically, for any meal plan created you can view a breakdown of all the ingredients, so you can grab them on your next trip out to Tesco.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Or at least I would be able to if it worked. Which at the time of writing, it doesn’t - at least not for me. Selecting and adding the recipes works, but currently, they don’t save, meaning that I can’t actually view them later.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>I am supremely confident that this will be fixed in the near future.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Other great features include the ability to import recipes from Nextcloud Cookbook and Chowdown. You can tweak the colour scheme however you want and adjust the number of recipes per page using a simple slider.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>There are so many features, options and tweaks that I’m not going to list them here. Some of them work as intended. Some don’t yet.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Right now your recipes are visible to the entire world although unsurprisingly, the option to set them to completely private is ‘on the roadmap.’ There’s also an idea to automagically pull in nutrition information for meals which is due to appear pretty soon.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="conclusion">Mealie development has stopped on Raspberry Pi</h2>
<p>
<!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Mealie is smooth and polished and beautiful - with development progressing at breakneck speed. As it stands, Nextcloud Cookbook is still functionally better - it has automatically generated cooking clocks which are nice, and everything works as advertised.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>But I’m migrating my Cookbook recipes to Mealie now, and new recipes are created in Mealie rather than in Cookbook. It’s not yet feature complete, and as I keep stressing, not everything works - yet.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>But It’s very usable even in its current state. This is good because due to compatibility issues, development has stopped on ARM implementations of Mealie.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="tandoor-another-contender">Tandoor: Another contender</h2>
<p>
<!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Mealie isn’t the only alternative to cookbook. One which I haven’t yet tried on my own server, but which looks very promising is <a href="https://github.com/vabene1111/recipes">Tandoor Recipes</a>.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Tandoor has been around for a lot longer than Mealie and has many more features - including the ability to import from both Nextcloud cookbook and Mealie; generate shopping lists; and recipe scaling, which is fabulous - tell it how many people you’re cooking for and it will adjust the quantities for you.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>I haven’t installed it but I’ve had a quick go on the <a href="https://app.tandoor.dev">demo server</a>, and I’m impressed. Image and page loading was a bit slow, but without actually spinning up an instance myself, I can say whether that’s down the the app or down to the hosting.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>If you feel the need for something a little more stable than Mealie in its current state, and with more features than Cookbook, then Tandoor Recipes might be just what you’re looking for.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:image {"id":206,"sizeSlug":"large","linkDestination":"none"} --></p>
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><figure class="wp-image-206"><img loading="lazy" src="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/34/tandoor_recipes_default_interface-1024x578.jpg" alt="Tandoor recipes on a black background"  sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/34/responsive/tandoor_recipes_default_interface-1024x578-xs.jpg 300w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/34/responsive/tandoor_recipes_default_interface-1024x578-sm.jpg 480w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/34/responsive/tandoor_recipes_default_interface-1024x578-md.jpg 768w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/34/responsive/tandoor_recipes_default_interface-1024x578-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/34/responsive/tandoor_recipes_default_interface-1024x578-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/34/responsive/tandoor_recipes_default_interface-1024x578-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure></figure>
<p>
<!-- /wp:image --></p>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Install Immich on a Raspberry Pi and replace Google Photos</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Rutland</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://linuximpact.com/install-immich-on-a-raspberry-pi-and-replace-google-photos/"/>
        <id>https://linuximpact.com/install-immich-on-a-raspberry-pi-and-replace-google-photos/</id>
        <media:content url="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/32/woman-in-jeans-using-immich-on-a-tablet.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="Tips"/>
            <category term="Software"/>
            <category term="Self-hosted"/>
            <category term="Linux"/>
            <category term="Internet"/>
            <category term="Hardware"/>
            <category term="DIY"/>

        <updated>2023-11-10T11:17:44+00:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/32/woman-in-jeans-using-immich-on-a-tablet.jpg" alt="" />
                    Immich is an open source Google Photos clone that you can host yourself. Even if you don't know what you're doing, it shouldn't take you more than an afternoon, starting from scratch. This guide is meant to get you up and running as fast as&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/32/woman-in-jeans-using-immich-on-a-tablet.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Immich is an open source Google Photos clone that you can host yourself. Even if you don't know what you're doing, it shouldn't take you more than an afternoon, starting from scratch. This guide is meant to get you up and running as fast as possible.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="why-use-a-raspberry-pi-to-host-immich">Why use a Raspberry Pi to host Immich?</h2>
<p>
<!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Simple. A server is meant to be powered on 24 hours per day 365 days a year. A Pi consumes minimal electrical power, but has enough computing power to get the job done.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="what-you-need">What you need</h2>
<p>
<!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>A Raspberry Pi 4B - The 8GB version is best, but 4GB will do.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>An adequate USB-C power supply.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>An Ethernet cable - it's faster and better than WiFi</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>A high capacity USB SSD - Micro SD cards aren't great.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>A different computer on the same network.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>A domain name</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="steps-to-install-immich-on-your-raspberry-pi-4b">Steps to install Immich on your Raspberry Pi 4B</h2>
<p>
<!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>These steps are meant to be followed from the beginning, but if you're already set up, feel free to skip parts. We're assuming you're using a Windows desktop machine - because most people do.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading {"level":3} --></p>
<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="install-an-os-to-your-ssd">Install an OS to your SSD</h3>
<p>
<!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>The Raspberry Pi Imager tool can install a variety of operating systems. Download it <a href="https://downloads.raspberrypi.org/imager/imager_latest.exe">here</a>, and double click on the file to launch the installer. Once, it's installed, launch Raspberry Pi Imager from your start menu.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Click <strong>Choose OS</strong>, then <strong>Raspberry Pi OS (Other) > Raspberry Pi OS Lite (64 Bit)</strong>.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:image {"id":284,"sizeSlug":"large","linkDestination":"none"} --></p>
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><figure class="wp-image-284"><img loading="lazy" src="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/32/raspberry-pi-os-imager-with-raspberry-pi-os-lite-64-bit-highlighted-1024x455.jpg" alt="raspberry pi os imager with raspberry pi os lite (64 bit) highlighted"  sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/32/responsive/raspberry-pi-os-imager-with-raspberry-pi-os-lite-64-bit-highlighted-1024x455-xs.jpg 300w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/32/responsive/raspberry-pi-os-imager-with-raspberry-pi-os-lite-64-bit-highlighted-1024x455-sm.jpg 480w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/32/responsive/raspberry-pi-os-imager-with-raspberry-pi-os-lite-64-bit-highlighted-1024x455-md.jpg 768w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/32/responsive/raspberry-pi-os-imager-with-raspberry-pi-os-lite-64-bit-highlighted-1024x455-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/32/responsive/raspberry-pi-os-imager-with-raspberry-pi-os-lite-64-bit-highlighted-1024x455-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/32/responsive/raspberry-pi-os-imager-with-raspberry-pi-os-lite-64-bit-highlighted-1024x455-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure></figure>
<p>
<!-- /wp:image --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Next, click <strong>Choose Storage</strong>, and select your SSD.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Click the cog icon in the lower right of the app, and set the following.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:list --></p>
<ul><!-- wp:list-item --></p>
<li>A name for the pi - "pi" is good.</li>
<p>
<!-- /wp:list-item --></p>
<p><!-- wp:list-item --></p>
<li>Check the box for <strong>Enable SSH</strong></li>
<p>
<!-- /wp:list-item --></p>
<p><!-- wp:list-item --></p>
<li>A username and password combo</li>
<p>
<!-- /wp:list-item --></p>
<p><!-- wp:list-item --></p>
<li>Locale with the correct timezone</li>
<p>
<!-- /wp:list-item --></p>
<p><!-- wp:list-item --></p>
<li>A static IP address - most ISPs will provide one for free if you ask nicely.</li>
<p>
<!-- /wp:list-item --></ul>
<p>
<!-- /wp:list --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Click <strong>Save</strong>, then <strong>Write</strong>.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Imager will inform you when the OS has been written to your drive.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="assemble-your-server">Assemble your server</h2>
<p>
<!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Plug the SSD into one of the available USB3 ports, then connect the ethernet cable to a spare Ethernet port on your router, and the other end to your Pi's ethernet port.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>NB: depending on the type of SSD, you may need a powered USB hub in order to prevent crashes and failures.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Finally, plug your power supply into the Pi's USB-C socket.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="connect-to-your-pi-from-your-pc">Connect to your Pi from your PC</h2>
<p>
<!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Secure Shell (SSH) provides a secure way to access and manage network devices and servers over an unsecured network. If you're on Windows, the easiest way to use SSH is with a dedicated client such as PuTTY.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Download PuTTY, and install it in the usual way. Open PuTTY from your start menu.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>In the <strong>Host Name</strong> text box, type in the Pi hostname followed by .local.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>If, when configuring the image earlier, you named your Pi as "pi", you would enter:</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>pi.local</code></pre>
<p>
<!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Choose <strong>SSH</strong> as the connection type, then hit <strong>Open</strong>.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>You'll see a scary warning about the host's key, hit yes to add it to the registry.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>A new window will open prompting you to enter your username, then your password. Do it.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading {"level":3} --></p>
<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="prepare-your-pi">Prepare your Pi</h3>
<p>
<!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>There are a few things you need to do before you can install Immich on your Raspberry Pi. All you need to do is copy and paste the following commands, and enter your password when asked.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>It's probably important to note that when entering a password in the Linux terminal, you won't see any response on the screen. Don't worry about this - just type your password and press <strong>Enter</strong> when you're done.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>First off, you'll need to make sure all your packages are up to date:</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>sudo apt update && sudo apt upgrade</code></pre>
<p>
<!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Install and enable Apache:</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>sudo apt install apache2<restore-line-break>sudo systemctl start apache2<restore-line-break>sudo systemctl enable apache2</code></pre>
<p>
<!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>All done? Sweet. It's worthwhile enabling some Apache modules. You won't need them all to install and use Immich, but they're useful to have:</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>sudo a2enmod rewrite http2 proxy proxy_http proxy_http2 proxy_wstunnel</code></pre>
<p>
<!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Now you need to install and enable Docker - a tool for managing containers:</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>sudo apt install docker.io<restore-line-break>sudo systemctl start apache2<restore-line-break>sudo systemctl enable apache2</code></pre>
<p>
<!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Add your user to the Docker group:</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>sudo usermod -aG docker pi</code></pre>
<p>
<!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>If your username is something other than "pi", use that instead.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Your membership of the Docker group won't take effect until you log out then back in again.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>exit</code></pre>
<p>
<!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>...will log you out. Log in again with PuTTY.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Docker Compose is a tool that makes managing Docker containers even easier. Unfortunately the version available in the standard repositories isn't up-to-date.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Manually install a recent version of Docker Compose, by pasting the following commands one at a time:</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>wget https://github.com/docker/compose/releases/download/v2.21.0/docker-compose-linux-aarch64<restore-line-break>mv docker-compose-linux-aarch64 /usr/local/bin/docker-compose<restore-line-break>sudo chmod +x /usr/local/bin/docker-compose<restore-line-break></code></pre>
<p>
<!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Finally, you need to find your local IP address. Run:</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>hostname -I</code></pre>
<p>
<!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>You'll see a lit of numbers, with eacher group of four separated by dots, for instance, "192.168.1.45". Your Pi's local IP address is the first on the list. Write it down for later.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="install-immich-on-your-pi">Install Immich on your Pi</h2>
<p>
<!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:image {"id":286,"sizeSlug":"large","linkDestination":"none"} --></p>
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><figure class="wp-image-286"><img loading="lazy" src="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/32/immich-web-interface-1024x514.jpg" alt="immich web interface showing memories and photos from today"  sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/32/responsive/immich-web-interface-1024x514-xs.jpg 300w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/32/responsive/immich-web-interface-1024x514-sm.jpg 480w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/32/responsive/immich-web-interface-1024x514-md.jpg 768w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/32/responsive/immich-web-interface-1024x514-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/32/responsive/immich-web-interface-1024x514-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/32/responsive/immich-web-interface-1024x514-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure></figure>
<p>
<!-- /wp:image --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>The hard work is done, and it's time to install Immich.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Create a directory for Immich, and a directory for your uploads:</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>mkdir immich && mkdir immich_uploads</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Move into the immich directory and download the Docker Compose file, and the environment file:</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>wget https://github.com/immich-app/immich/releases/latest/download/docker-compose.yml<restore-line-break>wget -O .env https://github.com/immich-app/immich/releases/latest/download/example.env</code></pre>
<p>
<!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Edit the environment file using the nano text editor:</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>nano .env</code></pre>
<p>
<!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Find the upload location section and change it to read:</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>UPLOAD_LOCATION=~/immich_uploads/</code></pre>
<p>
<!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Save and exit nano with <strong>Ctrl + O</strong> then <strong>Ctrl +X</strong>.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>The following command will download docker images, and start the containers for Immich:</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>docker-compose up -d</code></pre>
<p>
<!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>This will take some time. Go take the dogs for a walk, or do your shopping.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>When you return, open a browser on your PC, and in the url bar, enter:</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>your-pi-local-ip-address:2286</code></pre>
<p>
<!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>...substituting "your-pi-local-ip-address" for the actual local IP address you noted earlier. Click on the Get Started button and create the admin user by entering an email address and password. It doesn't have to be your real email address, and to be honest, it's probably better if it isn't.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Well done. Immich is up and running, but there are a few more things to do before you can start using it as a Google Photos alternative.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="make-your-immich-server-accessible-from-anywhere">Make your Immich server accessible from anywhere</h2>
<p>
<!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>You should already own a domain name. Visit your registrar, and locate the <strong>DNS</strong> or <strong>Advanced DNS </strong>section. Delete any records already set, and create a new one.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Set the host as @ and the value as your home IP address. Set the TTL value as low as you can.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>This will ensure that requests to your domain name are forwarded to your home IP address. You'll also need to ensure your router knows what to do with the requests.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Your router admin page is usually accessible by typing 192.168.1.1 into the address bar. If not, check the side of the router which will give you the correct address along with the default admin password.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Log into your router and look for a section called port forwarding or port management. Create a new entry for ports 80 and 443 – setting the value to your Pi's local IP address. Enter your domain name, and you should see the default Apache placeholder page.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Back on the Pi, create a config file for Apache:</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>cd /etc/apache2/sites-available/<restore-line-break>nano immich.conf</code></pre>
<p>
<!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>In the new file, paste the following text, making sure to substitute your actual domain name:</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>In the new file, paste the following:</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code><VirtualHost *:80><restore-line-break>ServerName your_domain.com<restore-line-break>ProxyPass / http://127.0.0.1:2283/<restore-line-break>ProxyPassReverse / http:/127.0.0.1:2283/<restore-line-break>ProxyPreserveHost On<restore-line-break></VirtualHost></code></pre>
<p>
<!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Save and exit nano again, and enter the following:</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>sudo a2ensite immich.conf<restore-line-break>sudo service apache2 restart</code></pre>
<p>
<!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>You should now be able to access your Immich instance by typing your domain name into any browser.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>That's great, but you're not secured by TLS, meaning your traffic could be intercepted by a Person-in-the-middle attack. It's unlikely, but it's better to be safe than sorry.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Fortunately, there's a handty tool called Certbot which can fetch and install security certificates for you, as well as upgrading connections to the more secure HTTPS protocol.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Install Certbot with:</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>sudo apt install software-properties-common<restore-line-break>sudo apt update<restore-line-break>sudo add-apt-repository ppa:certbot/certbot<restore-line-break>sudo apt-get install python3-certbot-apache</code></pre>
<p>
<!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Run certbot with:</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>sudo certbot</code></pre>
<p>
<!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Answer the questions, then restart Apache again with:</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>sudo service apache2 restart</code></pre>
<p>
<!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>That's it. You're done. Congratulations! Now install the apps on your phone.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>How to use ChatGPT 3.5 from your terminal without API Keys using tgpt</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Rutland</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://linuximpact.com/how-to-use-chatgpt-35-from-your-terminal-without-api-keys-using-tgpt/"/>
        <id>https://linuximpact.com/how-to-use-chatgpt-35-from-your-terminal-without-api-keys-using-tgpt/</id>
        <media:content url="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/31/woman-using-tgpt-on-a-laptop.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="Tips"/>
            <category term="Terminal"/>
            <category term="Software"/>
            <category term="Linux"/>
            <category term="DIY"/>
            <category term="CLI"/>

        <updated>2023-11-10T11:17:44+00:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/31/woman-using-tgpt-on-a-laptop.jpg" alt="" />
                    AI chatbots are a wonder of the modern age and can assist with everything from coding to poetry. But accessing ChatGPT usually means signing up for an account. tgpt is a terminal interface that doesn't require an account or API key, and allows you to&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/31/woman-using-tgpt-on-a-laptop.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>AI chatbots are a wonder of the modern age and can assist with everything from coding to poetry. But accessing ChatGPT usually means signing up for an account. tgpt is a terminal interface that doesn't require an account or API key, and allows you to use ChatGPT 3.5 without leaving your terminal.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="why-use-tgpt">Why use tgpt?</h2>
<p>
<!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>When you sign up to use ChatGPT all of your queries, conversations, idle musings, and boundary-pushing questions are tied to your account.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Aside from the obvious privacy risks associated with using ChatGPT, a transcript of all your interactions could prove to be embarrassing - especially if you use the chatbot for writing difficult emails, cut your medical insurance premiums by using ChatGPT as a therapist, or use AI to prognosticate the future.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Using ChatGPT through the web interface is a far from ideal experience, and while there are already CLI tools that let you use ChatGPT from the Linux terminal, these require you to use an API key - a process that both complicates setting up the tool, and ensures that OpenAI can associate your queries with you - even if you use a VPN to hide your IP address.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>By installiing tgpt, you get the convenience of using ChatGPT in your terminal, and you don't need to provide an API key or account details. You can use tgpt wherever you are, and even access it from behind a VPN.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="how-to-install-tgpt-on-linux">How to install tgpt on Linux</h2>
<p>
<!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:image {"id":276,"sizeSlug":"large","linkDestination":"none"} --></p>
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><figure class="wp-image-276"><img loading="lazy" src="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/31/install-tgpt-with-go-1024x439.jpg" alt="terminal output for installing tgpt with go"  sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/31/responsive/install-tgpt-with-go-1024x439-xs.jpg 300w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/31/responsive/install-tgpt-with-go-1024x439-sm.jpg 480w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/31/responsive/install-tgpt-with-go-1024x439-md.jpg 768w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/31/responsive/install-tgpt-with-go-1024x439-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/31/responsive/install-tgpt-with-go-1024x439-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/31/responsive/install-tgpt-with-go-1024x439-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure></figure>
<p>
<!-- /wp:image --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>The easiest way to install tgpt on Linux is with Go, so <a href="https://www.makeuseof.com/how-to-install-go-on-linux/">make sure you have Go installed</a> before you begin.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Now you can use Go to install tgpt:</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>go install github.com/aandrew-me/tgpt@latest</code></pre>
<p>
<!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Go will install tgpt to <strong>~/go/bin/tgpt</strong></p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>If you want to easily use tgpt from any terminal location, you should create a symbolic link:</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>sudo ln -s ~/go/bin/tgpt /usr/bin/tgpt</code></pre>
<p>
<!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>You can start tgpt by typing:</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>tgpt</code></pre>
<p>
<!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>...wherever you are in the terminal.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Unfortunately, this won't work on Windows, and is yet another addition to<a href="https://linuximpact.com/linux-vs-windows-which-is-best-for-your-pc/" data-type="link" data-id="https://linuximpact.com/linux-vs-windows-which-is-best-for-your-pc/"> why Linux is better than Windows</a>.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="use-tgpt-to-get-chatgpt-in-your-terminal">Use tgpt to get ChatGPT in your terminal</h2>
<p>
<!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:image {"id":277,"sizeSlug":"large","linkDestination":"none"} --></p>
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><figure class="wp-image-277"><img loading="lazy" src="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/31/tgpt-in-interactive-mode-1024x636.jpg" alt="tgpt in interactive mode showing a haiku about dogs and one about cats"  sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/31/responsive/tgpt-in-interactive-mode-1024x636-xs.jpg 300w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/31/responsive/tgpt-in-interactive-mode-1024x636-sm.jpg 480w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/31/responsive/tgpt-in-interactive-mode-1024x636-md.jpg 768w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/31/responsive/tgpt-in-interactive-mode-1024x636-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/31/responsive/tgpt-in-interactive-mode-1024x636-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://linuximpact.com/media/posts/31/responsive/tgpt-in-interactive-mode-1024x636-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure></figure>
<p>
<!-- /wp:image --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Using tgpt couldn't be easier. If you have a one of query or request for ChatGPT, and, for instance, want the chatbot to write a haiku about dogs, you'd enter:</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>tgpt 'Write a haiku about dogs'</code></pre>
<p>
<!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Remember to surround your query with quote marks or tgpt will return a response for the first word only. Without quote marks in the above example, tgpt will respond as if you queried:</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>tgpt write</code></pre>
<p>
<!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Not so useful.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>tgpt is most useful in interactive mode. To start tgpt in interactive mode, use the <strong>i</strong> flag:</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>tgpt -i</code></pre>
<p>
<!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>This allows you to conduct a complete conversation with ChatGPT, and its responses will be flavoured by your previous replies.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>As with the web interface, your conversations can be long, meandering, and cover many topics.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>You can can force tgpt to forget the chat ID with:</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>tgpt -f</code></pre>
<p>
<!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Other useful flags include:</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>-s Generate and Execute shell commands. (Experimental)<br>-c Generate Code. (Experimental)<br>-q Gives response back without loading animation<br>-w Gives response back as a whole text<br>-v Print version<br>-h Print help message<br>-m Start multi-line interactive mode<br>-u Update program</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Unlike with the ChatGPT web interface, you can use tgpt even when your hiding behind a VPN. This doesn't mean you can get away with naughty queries, though. Ask tgpt an inappropriate query and it'll respond that it's unable to assist you</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="is-tgpt-too-good-to-be-true">Is tgpt too good to be true?</h2>
<p>
<!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>In a word, yes.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>tgpt is an awesome and fun way to access ChatGPT from your terminal, but it isn't truly a way to do it without API keys.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Instead of using your API key, tgpt uses the programme author's ChatGPT API key. Looking through the Github repository, you can see that the API key changes regularly. Presumably, this is because providing tgpt is a breach of ChatGPT terms of service.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>If tgpt stops working for some reason, updating it with:</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:code --></p>
<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>tgpt -u</code></pre>
<p>
<!-- /wp:code --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>...should get it going again.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Having said that, it's unlikely that tgpt will continue working forever.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>In the meantime, enjoy it while it lasts.</p>
<p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
